<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An address to the hopeful young gentry of England in some strictures on the most dangerous vices incident to their age and quality / by a perfect honourer of their worth.</title>
            <author>Perfect honourer of their worth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26401</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36717</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15993053</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15993053</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104697</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26401)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104697)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1083:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An address to the hopeful young gentry of England in some strictures on the most dangerous vices incident to their age and quality / by a perfect honourer of their worth.</title>
                  <author>Perfect honourer of their worth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 114 [i.e. 141], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.C. for G. Walbancke, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ethics.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ADDRESS To the Hopeful Young GENTRY OF ENGLAND. IN Some Strictures on the moſt dangerous Vices incident to their Age and Quality.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Mors fera, Parce precor, vitam anticipare vel ipſam;</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t moriatur Homo, ſit precor ipſe priús.</l>
               <l> 
                  <hi>Couleius</hi> noſter De Salviâ.</l>
               <l>Cur moriatur-Cui Salvia creſcit?</l>
            </q>
            <p>By a perfect Honourer of their Worth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. C.</hi> for <hi>G. Walbancke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop neer <hi>Grays-Inn-Gate</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed> Rob. Grove <hi>R.P.D.</hi> Epiſc. Lond. a ſac. Domeſt.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>Mart. <hi>26.
1669.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Nobly Accompliſhed, AND Honourably Deſcended
<hi>John Burgoyne</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the midst of the giddy and rapid turnings of the Affairs of this World, the Malignity and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominancy of Vice, clowding and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing Reaſon, violently agitating the pureſt of its ſpirits and ſuccors into the ſame commotions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions: He that can ſtand ſteady <pb facs="tcp:104697:3"/>and immoveable is a greater Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, than could have been the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of <hi>Archimedes</hi> his bold Boaſt; That he would unfix this whole Globe of Earth, might be have but a footing off from it. For beſide his vanity to promiſe the uncentring of that vaſt Body and unweildy, when he could not give his own ſmall active Carcaſe one remove from it; He would have been as far to ſeek for a convenient diſtance and ſtation where to effect the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: So that thorough the incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and impoſsibility of his <hi>poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum,</hi> the grand deſign muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily fall to the ground, as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely as himſelf was erelong cast down, to meaſure his own lines and narrow dimenſions in the Dust. But granting it a demonſtration, I muſt <pb facs="tcp:104697:3"/>pay far greater Admiration and Eſteem to thoſe brave Souls, who when the whole courſe of Nature is under impetuous motions and tumults remain unconcern'd and fixt, and, by the conduct of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Virture, retain their Sobriety and Prudence, when all about them is mad, and under the fatal hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the great Diſturbers of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, or the furious Tempeſts of their own uncontrouled paſsions: This
'tis to bear up a manly head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Ruines, though the whole Fabrick of the World be ſinking, and rowling into one Confuſion.</p>
            <p>That the ſlender ſupports of theſe few Lines are oppoſ'd againſt theſe threatned miſchiefs of bolder Vice, with ambition to act the part of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Atlas</hi> (for our declining Age <pb facs="tcp:104697:4"/>ſeems to want more than One) would be a preſumption I need not acquit my ſelf from, by aſſuring you I dwell not ſo much abroad, and from the notice of the dangers menacing my own Cottage: And indeed I here expect the whole world to be my Compurgators, and fearing no ſuch Calamity that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one will excuſe me that Labour, and as readily engage against any other ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaker. The truth is [Sir] theſe ſhort reflexes on Vice do exceedingly enhanſe to me the Beauty and Dowry of Virtue; the more I contemplate the vacui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and deformities of that, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire to find not ſo much as the leaſt ſhadow of either in this; And I am willing to proclaim aloud, That Virtue alone is that noble and <pb facs="tcp:104697:4"/>undaunted generoſity; which not any ſingle Engineer, but were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very vicious perſon an <hi>Archime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> with all their Stratagems and force they could not in the leaſt ſhake or undermine. And where ſhould I expect, however wiſh, to find this Gallantry of Spirit, if not among our Nobleſs? I look on them to be the Spirituous bloud of the Body Politick; not their Purpurate deſcent alone, but the unqueſtionable verity that the Bloud is the vitals of the Creature warrants my aſſertion; and it would be an ungrateful Argument to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince it, from the infallible approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Death, once enterr'd here, makes upon all the fortreſſes of the Garriſon, in every tide the bloud beats up, to and from the <pb facs="tcp:104697:5"/>Heart. The fortyfying therefore of this <hi>Archeus,</hi> may it be as cordial and acceptable, as if I now brought ſome nobler Liquor to be transfuſ'd into the veins, and drein'd off the ſheepiſh and vitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line qualities ſo long fed upon and imbib'd, that, though we ſcorn the cloathing, betray the ſound of Wool in our language.</p>
            <p>But Sir I must stop here to meet your wonder, when under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding perfectly my temperament, you ſee this cloſe conception expoſ'd and enduring the ſight of the Sun, and every ones readineſs in Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognomy: and that He you know me to be, when the World can be no more advantaged by his mean capacity, than he is like to be by its unexpected kindneſs; will yet <pb facs="tcp:104697:5"/>put himſelf under the power of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from it: why he is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſit ſtill in private digeſting his reſentments of the follies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, with the freedom they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him to be quiet? and if ſome will ever be found doing amiſs, what ſhould make him do worſe, to ſay he likes it not? He will firſt tell you every day produces ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as ſtrange as this, and what may equally be the object of your wonder; unleſs you are wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from it, and He from ſaying more of it. But if He much more wonder at this himſelf and (if the regard He cannot diſſemble for himſelf would permit) do hugely condemn himſelf and it: Will you or any other like him, or it, the better? If neither, Sir believe it, <pb facs="tcp:104697:6"/>he will keep a little more good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſtore for himſelf, which ſhall make him eſteem no better of himſelf and the world, than if there were no relation intervening; He means ſo much to favour himſelf, that that ſhall do him as little hurt as he can do it good. And if you look for your friend, Sir, he is not yet turn'd Anchorite, he will ſooner be a Pilgrim with good Company, and the excellent Guide he is lately acquainted with. Nor are his reſentments in fear of Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion next Spring; Nay he hopes to be as ſerene in the Canicular daies, as now, when the humors are cloſe with the Earth lockt up in the cold and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent embraces of the Snow. And let this clear him from being thought too invective to the evils of our times; that as he is ſenſible of a monſtrous <pb facs="tcp:104697:6"/>conflux of inſtant vices, his thoughts are calm, and pen but mild, to thoſe fears he has of the next age, in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be oreſpread with the Superfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of that Impiety, which will be too obdurate to feel the edge of a Satyr.</p>
            <p>Sir all but your ſelf will now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect large Encomiums to recommend you to the view of the multitude; But <hi>I</hi> am ſenſible they ſtand but ready to devour you, and this I call you to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize For your ſelf, Sir, I averre not ſo much Jealouſie over your inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to theſe vices, as Hopes that your life will be a fair copy of all Virtues, preſents you to this place, to ſupply the draught I ſhould haue added to them: and may your Auſpicious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings continue me in acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my defects and tenuity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terring <pb facs="tcp:104697:7"/>my pen from entring on the Commendations will be your due. And for your Family, it is ſo illuſtrious, that <hi>I</hi> ſhall be taxed by thoſe that would find nothing good in it, for da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to affix this Name to ſo mean a Front: and they will leave you in haſt to come and revenge themſelves upon me, if I cannot eſcape their ſtomach. However be pleaſed my wiſhes, and well wiſht directions may be favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly interpreted by your Noble mind, and all of your truly noble qu lity.</p>
            <p>And Sir, for your friend, pray wiſh him well alſo, now faln to be employ'd in ſuch a publick Character; for you cannot tell what change he may not dare venture next in his life, (if you will with him ſuppoſe it of his Life, which every day changeth; not of himſelf and his vow'd conſtancy and <pb facs="tcp:104697:7"/>integrity) for there muſt, and will be found ſome ſo fooliſh, as not to fear the Printers nor Readers Preſs they are to paſs, any more than others doe Matrimony: and there may be Fatali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be pleaded for that alſo; which to fear is the next way to the curſe of continuing a Miſerable Life, out of all hopes of a kind Reprieve of Death to cut the halter of our fears. And me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I am now acting my own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting; and have two words to ſay for my ſelf before the laſt Farewel: wherein (Pardon the digreſsion) I ſeem to repreſent many of thoſe we have ſeen too much perſonating a publick (not to ſay republick) death, as if their deaths too were to be none of their own: not unlike to me they appear to the poor Widow, who went out to gather two ſticks to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <pb facs="tcp:104697:8"/>a ſmall cake, that they may at leaſt dye with a good morſel in their mouths. But not to forget to leave off, though I doe it leſs formally: For firſt I will not ſupplicate your favour, no more than expect your thanks, for being prolix, but tell you my deſign is honeſt, and an effect of my Honour to your Name and Perſon. Next I know not how to intreat a good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or pardon of the Language, only aſſure you, I took what words I thought moſt full and near to my Conceptions; and I can ſooner alter the natural Tone of my voice, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit any others, than chuſe to fall into the Rectifiers or Body-makers hands, and ſuffer my Mind to be pinched and ſhaped into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of anothers dreſs and Mode of expreſsion. I ſhall but add, that <pb facs="tcp:104697:8"/>all of it is but a Chriſtmá Letter: And you know we are allow'd our Maſquerades, and longer feſtivous entertains of a Carnival; So as you will admit it over your threſhold, when I tell you under the vizour in a whiſper, That I am none other than Your very known Servant</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January, 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 166
8/9.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104697:9"/>
            <head>AN ADDRESS To the Hopefull Young Gentry OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE you are now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring upon thoſe years, which entitle you the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hopes of <hi>England,</hi> and their faireſt Care and Charge; from whom is expected the ſtrength and honour of your Age, the ſecurity and glory of the Nation: It cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy conſideration to Adviſe, by what generous means the old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown of our Anceſtors may be vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104697:10"/>from the threatned Evils of thoſe dangerous Vices, which, ſpringing up with the young Nobleſs of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, enervate their native vigor, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plume their Nobility; and in a vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous combination attempt to ſtrangle our <hi>Hercules</hi> in it's very infancy.</p>
            <p>Your birth was in the midſt of buſie and tumultuous Times, wherein you may remember, and could not but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſome of the later grand cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophes, in which part of your ſeveral families eminently acting, from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious engagings and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cceſſes of thoſe your relations you ſtill received ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Impreſſions on your green years; and in thoſe early days took in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rge Map of the World in a ſmal Compaſs: You have ſeen enough in your ſphere to make you early commence Men, and furniſh you with notices beyond the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearches of former Hiſtories. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be reckoned among the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacies of mankind, that ſo many are found to complain of their peculiar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunacy, to be caſt into ſuch a ſtirring <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104697:10"/>and unquiet Age as we have lived in: Whereas an Heroic ſpirit and virtue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteems it a proper exerciſe &amp; teſt of it's worth, from ſo great revolutions acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring withal a knowledge and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the admirable occurrences, we turn many years Chronicles to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with: there having met ſo rare and quick a conflux of ſignal mercies and judgments together, that we may judge them deſign'd by Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, either to make the utmoſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment to reſuſcitate a lethargic peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and reſtore Spirits in the Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of Elyxirs: Or as the Stage is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way fulleſt and crowded with diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es at the winding up the Play, that the World it ſelf near a period, is to fill up it's ſhort duration with an Epitome of all the wonderful events of paſt Ages, if not laboring to exceed them all in delivery of a new world of Prodigies, e're it be made the greateſt by it's own conflagration.</p>
            <p>But among all the unhappy Ones we have liv'd to ſee, none is ſo ſtupendous <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104697:11"/>as their unſucceſsfulneſs; That when an hand from high has been exerted in all the amazing Methods of Providence, we have clos'd our Eyes with a Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant obſtinacy againſt the cleareſt evidencies and acknowledgments of a Deity; and been ſo miſerably incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as to dare the Divine Vengeance to farther proofs of it's Power and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in our utter confuſion. Thus of old, <hi>Veſuvius</hi> could not ſatisfie ſome unreaſonable <hi>Curioſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> but by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to it's fewel, or the difficulty of a receſs; whence they brought the ſcars and ſtigmas of their folly, who hoped to pry and wade through ſuch clouds of ſmoak and gulfs of Fire. You are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to contraſt with a ſtupidly opining Age, which, having forfeited the right uſe of it's Reaſon, will deſperatly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all to the hazard, rather than ſeem to be without it; and ſtumbling at the plain, moſt familiar, and lucid Reſolves of Reaſon and Nature, will yet blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſay to ranſack all their moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe treaſures, and diſcuſs the <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104697:11"/>Sacred Myſteries Infinitely tranſcending either.</p>
            <p>But the malice of this evil will aſſault you moſt dangerouſly, by corrupting all the ſound Rules of Morality in your converſe; and having conform'd your manners to the licentiouſneſs it practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, you muſt be forc'd to eſpouſe thoſe principles which will patronize your exorbitancies. And this is a very inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuative debauching of the mind, a Conqueſt without the formalities of an attaque, which ſerve to alarm us againſt the Enemy. There are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the moſt pernicious habits which our young Gallants Indulge, which ſeem to me the infallible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſticks of their ruine, and the fate of the common Body; Againſt which I am to fortifie you, as thoſe that by their very familiarity and obviouſneſs are become more inimical and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, gathering ſtrength by not being oppos'd, and by our long deſuetude from the contrary renour of unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd Virtue; which if you admit to <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104697:12"/>become the Arbitres of your Life and Conceptions, will render the various aſpects of every Age as pleaſant and uſeful to your ſteady and clear optics, as they are confuſive and unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all other ſpectators.</p>
            <p>He that expects after a Deluge the ſame vernancy diſpoſition and order, the ſoil was before adorn'd with; may alſo hope the Inundations of war will aſſwage with the eaſie and ſilent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of Peace; and that the next Age will, without interruption, proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and perfect the deſigns only, of their quiet Grandfathers. How much of this is like truth, let us judge by what all former Times record, if our own be yet too near the ſeed time, and the next be to inherit the Crop. But this has as much truth as need be own'd; That if the Virtues of their progenitors be defaced by the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding audaciouſneſs of the ſword, their Vices however will never want foſtering by the next Generations: Hence what were but the expoſed <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104697:12"/>ſtoln off-ſpring of former years, are the Legitimacies of later; and we have no copy left ſo foul, which too ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly tranſcribing Vice do's not every day out-blur. You may therefore, if you will, owe the torrent of our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities to the Time when nothing was unlawful; The Fountain is too deeply emboſom'd in our Natures, to lay ſo far off. But it is not impoſſible to trace it from it's earlieſt footſteps, and where it begins to ſpring into a ſtream; but that ſo ſullyed in the puddle it flows from, that you will conclude it to be rather one ditch and channel of mire. And it can be no other, that ſcarcely can be ſaid to riſe out of the lap of Sloath; On the Baſis whereof might Vice be fixed, it would raiſe it's Pillars, and even ſtop you here from farther enquiries after Honour and Glory, to ſleep out the remaining bale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful minutes of Life in</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104697:13"/>
               <head>IDLENESS,</head>
               <p>The Capital of thoſe Indulgencies, that conſpire the delivery up of our hopeful Youth, bound hand and foot into the vaſſalage and torures of impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Vice: the puniſhment of him who was bound to an heated Stag, that could neither command himſelf nor the ſwift Beaſt; but tyed and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active, yet ran all the Stages of his Bearers excurſions, and was held faſt to all it's petulant vagaries: Such is the hurry of reſtleſs paſſions in the Idle Soul, through the many regions of Phanſie, and boundleſs Appetite; till it be tyr'd and fall down in ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert of obſcene darkneſs. The Idle perſon is the only common Hackney, and, having no employ of his own to work off Time and his faculties, ſtands ready to let out himſelf Poſt, on the eaſie rates of the next ſtirring device and lubency. A Play, a Ball, a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, a Glaſs of Wine engage his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104697:13"/>Soul as profoundly in contemplation of his dawning felicity, as the <hi>Turks</hi> Zeal is enſpirited by their brutiſh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe. But We compaſſionate theſe poor Infidels, whoſe knowledge is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd with the brandiſh'd Sword; and perhaps were ours forbidden on as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal curioſity, it would become more deſirable. While though, we every day make bold plantations (how ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully I will not adjuſt) upon every Creek and Point of Philoſophy, and outbid all Antiquity on the fair terms We proffer knowledge: to ſee the refined and moſt improvable part of our own land uncultivated, the Youth and ſtrength of our Nation lay fallow, and only ſhoot forth into thoſe ſpungy Muſhroms and Wild-daiſies, their ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brain makes grow into it's entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; is enough to perſwade us that true knowledge is as inacceſſible as the Tree of Life, and that Our Age is moſt unfortunate to be debarr'd the proper ſcrutinies and direct approaches to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it. For certainly knowledge and <pb n="10" facs="tcp:104697:14"/>Wiſdom it ſelf is ſtill the ſame pure and ſubtile concentration of light; It cannot as to it's real worth and luſtre be depretiated, and would alway de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the utmoſt inſudation, the beſt of our Oyl and Labor in it's acqueſt. It muſt be therefore the diſmal diſaſter of our time, that denies us all poſſibility of diſcovery, where this lucid Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid is erected, and how we may come under it's vital influences. Were we not thus loſt with the <hi>Eden</hi> we have loſt, without doubt we ſhould not be contented with our low and puerile attempts after it; But awake from our ſluggiſh velleities, vigorouſly to ſtring and ſtrain our minds, to work ſome other furniture for them, beſide Couches and Pallets; we would break open ſome way to let in the bright rays of Knowledge and Virtue, and not imagine we had lamps given us only to hang up againſt the wall, to drowze, or be penſively befotted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them: while nothing but the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maera's, follies and ſhadows of a dream, <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104697:14"/>haunt the thin Ghoſts in their living Sepulchres, till theſe are commuted for a thicker, but not more heavy or uſeleſs Arch of Stone.</p>
               <p>But to free us from the inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this kind of dead-ſleep, and excite us to a noble inquiſition after Virtue and Science; let the whole World be convinc'd, that they are as acceſſible as immutable, nor do on any parts of the Univerſe vary their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, nor can be Retrograde on the Dial of any time. Our age is as freely irradiated with their beams, as with that benignity of the Sun, which ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our Anceſtors Cucumers, and now ſtripes and paints our Melons; 'tis our want alone of riſing will not ſuffer us to ſee day. While beſide Man (the leſſer ſcheme of the Creation) the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt portion of Mankind (I mean thoſe of your degree) and the Soul of Man (it's noble Heaven-born inhabitant) nothing is found idle in nature. She is every where, and continually, pregnant with new labors, and productions: ſee <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104697:15"/>how in the Vegetative World not a ſpire of Graſs creeps out of the Earth, but is elevating its head ſtill nearer to Heaven: In the Senſitive the choiceſt Animals receive our commands, and execute our drudgeries: That <hi>Coloſs</hi> of life, the Elephant has its underſtanding, ſtrength, and ſervice apportioned to its bulk; and among Inſects, the very Fly and Ant make a ſupplement to their cloſe dimenſions, in their wonderful agility and induſtry; by which they fill up an equal ſpace with vaſteſt bodies. In the fabric and conſtitution of Man, ſhe is ſtill buſied in accumulation of ſimilary, or exporting uſeleſs and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordant particles. Life it ſelf ſeems to be but the reſult, and harmony of an even-flowing motion; and that
<hi>Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maton</hi> which keeps pace with every ſtep of time, ſtriking all its own minuteſt and remoteſt wheels with a regular ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liency, tells us lowdly by the pulſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pillow, that we were not born to ſlumber away our haſty time and life; which hold more of a Race than
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104697:15"/>walk in their motion and tendency to their laſt pawſe and reſt. Nor does Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with ſo much exactneſs elaborate and exalt the ſpirits in the body, inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to put off and loſe their name and nature, by being blended and periſhing in an inſipid <hi>Caput mortuum;</hi> or as if they were ſo curiouſly contriv'd and deſign'd, only to officiate in that ſcul, once Head of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; which rival'd <hi>Jove,</hi> but ſtoop'd below his very Eagle when turn'd into the device of a <hi>Moſt Auguſt Fly-Trap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can you have leiſure to admire e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough at that impertinency, which would ſummon the utmoſt skill and conſort of Muſic to play his Dormouſe aſleep? or would to Oriental Bezoar and Ambar diſſolve Gold and Pearl, to maintain a Mole? To no higher archievements ſerve the fair Titles, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, and Complexions of a great part of Mankind; beſide theſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is intelligible about them, nor can more be ſaid of them: ſo near to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing do they ſhrink, whoſe ſouls lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104697:16"/>under the irreparable decays of tabific inactivity; or are broken with pitiful low and ſordid lubencies of idle entertainments; wholly ſuperſeding thoſe brave actions, ſublime and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpeculations, which would infuſe the life of men into them, and render them, off Men, immortal. Thus their Heroic Progenitors traced Virtue and Honour, through all its intricate and dangerous mazes; and this was the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent they made to that high ſerenenes, where every Pearl of their Coronets was ſtellified: And this only high-way to Happineſs is ſtill as open, and more delightful than you imagine the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon deſcent to
<hi>Avernus.</hi> And indeed it can be no other than the very dregs of Idleneſs that can ſink the ſpirit (or may I not rather ſay, the Sediment of a ſoul?) below all handſome action, in ſuch an age as we live, which pretends to ſuch extraordinary Knowledge and Politeneſs; however muſt be moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for thoſe Grand Actions to be enroll'd in it, wherein Poſterity will <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104697:16"/>imagine none could be born but to ſome laborious part.</p>
               <p>Had we the generoſity which did alway breath with
<hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpirits, it would be ſo far from being extinguiſh'd in ignoble ſilence, and limited to the narrow ſtage of our own Iland, that it would break forth and diſplay its valour through all parts of the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earth. Have we no <hi>Meſſieurs de Villa, Fevillade,</hi> or St.
<hi>Mont-brun</hi> kindled with the ſparks of honor, that will flie to the ſuccors of that Chiſtian Garriſon (before whoſe walls more blood has been ſhed, than would ſerve for Cement to a far greater City) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than expire at home, as unknown as their Tombs will be to the <hi>Candiots!</hi> Certainly That place is now the faireſt Field of Honor, which has ſo long been the Chriſtians ſtrongeſt ſhield (under their great Captain and Prince) againſt Infidels, and it will be worthy learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with how vaſt expenſe of Treaſure, and prodigality of Lives, they ſtudy to defend their dearer Country. And <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104697:17"/>in the long ſtory of that ſingle Siege you will read all the old admired <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Courage, Conduct, and Felicity; which will be ſo ſignaliz'd to after times, that our lateſt Nephews will take a Voyage only to viſit its vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ruines; wherein are now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed thoſe gallant Souls, that have ſhaken off the ſoftneſs, and ſtupifying pleaſures of Eaſe, with the grim ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Death, to ſacrifice all in ſo glorious a Quarrel, and for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſecurity. Can we lie immerſed in wanton Idleneſs, when Chriſtianity is concerned for her battered Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks, that ſuffer again the Siege of <hi>Rhodes</hi> more nearly; and that in ſuch ſanguinary Scenes and Tragedies, as the very naming them will fright the young Gallants out of the Pit?</p>
               <p>Where being brought by my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, I do not much admire to ſee the Theatres crowded with our Idle Spectators; the hours here ſpent are a tolerable exemption from lewder diverſions, and with ſome obtain the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104697:17"/>credit of a School diſcipline, periodic Lectures, and Academic exercitations; which teach as much gravity and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, as they think can amount to neceſſary aphoriſms, to regulate their own lives by, and be diagnoſtic of all others. I may not envy the Dramatic Ingenioſos the Empire they here ſway over Wit, nor the Models they give of the world, and the delectable variety, in which they ſerve up the humors that are abroad: May the Stage never want a florid Laureat to Chaſtize predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Vices, and troubleſome Follies; but ſo prudently and induſtriouſly, that they may no longer be fear'd to teach them. But I could wiſh our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſs would here alway admit the but neceſſary ceremony of a Taſter; that they may have its ſalubriouſneſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, before it take poſſeſſion of their Stomach, and it prove too late for an Antidote. But ſuppoſing the Stage leſs dangerous and nauſeous than ſome Pulpits; and that every day brought forth a work as conſummat as <pb n="18" facs="tcp:104697:18"/>Father <hi>Ben's:</hi> Yet I would advize them againſt their common frequenting Plays, if I took it not as an evicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they knew no more congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous advancement of their Noble fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; and were burthened with too long and empty parentheſes of Time. For, I conceive, whoever tranſmits his affections to be wrought on by every fiction the Poet engages them in, ſhall in a little time ceaſe to be Maſter over them, and they will be at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of every paſſionate Romantique: Or they will be ſo broken or extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, wholly by ſuch continued and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent efforts, that they will altogether be unſerviceable, if he loſe not all the due ſentiments of Nature: Either of which extreme is ſo palpable an imbecillity of mind, as need not be pointed at, for it too eaſily betrays it ſelf in dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe? Greater inconveniences you may hear continually nurs'd up at the Stage, and fear worſe; unleſs it be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly purg'd and refin'd.</p>
               <p>But indeed what place, time, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104697:18"/>is not poiſon'd in a dead Sea of Idleneſs, though they be never ſo free and innocent in their own diſpoſition? Virtue and Generoſity it ſelf coming but neer it, though but in a volatile thought or Action, is ſuddenly ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with the noyſome exhalations of this almoſt Stygian lake. I have heard in a very serene Oratory affirmed; that two parts of three, that are now ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenc'd under unquenchable flames, had thoſe firſt kindled here on earth, in the fire of their burning and impure luſt. However, it is ſcarce dubitable, that all thoſe miſerable Souls, now fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling up the regions of darkneſs, did firſt fit and adopt themſelves to that ſtate, by contracting a ſupine torpor and negligence of Spirit: For without controverſie, idleneſs lets in upon the Soul all the inundation of Vice, and is that unhappy plot oregrown with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weed and noxious burthen of the Earth; ſo that as ſome Gardens are a collection of the choyceſt and moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul Plants, this becomes a ſeminary of <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104697:19"/>all the horrid excreſcencies can grow out of a Dunghill.</p>
               <p>We indeed ſee ſome of active lives and full of buſineſſe fall into exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancies of as diſmal effects, as can be the off-ſpring of the dulleſt brain and hours: But you may not ſurmiſe this the genuine birth of any honorable or neceſſary employ. Thoſe publick ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits were to be commiſerated more than they who offered their lives as their Countries Victims of old, if there were any fatal connexion of Vice with their Offices; which are conſecrated as the very Rewards and Aſylums of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and are ſo many Thrones on which ſhe may diſplay and diſpenſe her So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign dignity and influences. No, I muſt believe any vices nouriſht under their protection to be the ſcrofulae, and luxuriant impetigos of fowl humors. They will prove the diſeaſe of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not the office; and entrench ſo much upon the borders of Idleneſs, that you will entertain the greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt that evill, which can
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104697:19"/>prevail upon the ſtrongeſt and nobleſt conſtitutions. For I grant that perſon to be fal'n beſide his buſineſſe, and to have quitted his own Station; that is at leiſure to contrive and perſue his private ſtratagems of ambition, avarice and malice. This is a degeneracy and corruption growing upon the Soul, by a vacation from his proper intendments of Time and Labor: while inſtead of his attendance on the ſteerage of the common Veſſel, the man is ſo idle as to row forth his own Cock-boat for ſhells and pebbles. But whatever ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and juſtifiable gratifications are here to be glean'd up, their Country would add their bleſſing to the heap, might it encourage every one nobly endowed to adapt himſelf and fortunes for the honor and ſervice of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. But let this Idleneſſe never bear the impudence to ſteal upon an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable preſence, it being as indecorous, as to ſee a rude clown cover'd near the Chair of State. And what diſtance that was to obſerve at Court, the very
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104697:20"/>proud and barbarous Turkiſh Sultans in their profeſſion and skill of ſome mechanic art ſtill teach us; and we may better learn from our late Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraigns Royal mouth, that He thought He could earn a Livelyhood were he ſo low reduc'd by any Trade he knew of, but making of Hangings: his Clemency will allow you the allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to any fair fence of the word: and his conſtant inſtructions to the Nobleſs craving his permiſſion to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, had this alway inſerted, to keep the beſt Company, and never be idle. May it therefore by ſo canonized an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample be baniſht all Societies, as that which wherever it comes is ſure to ſhut the man out of doors; For 'tis the man of buſineſſe gives denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and life to the world: And many an Age will be buried in oblivion, as ſilently as if it had loſt an entire ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of mankind, and all that was worthy recording.</p>
               <p>Idleneſs may it once be expell'd; I dare promiſe we ſhall obviate two ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104697:20"/>which become our mortal afflictions, and almoſt immortal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints; Our unreaſonable diſſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and decay of Trade. Idle peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſuch as have none of their own create buſineſſe for all about them; and their proper concerns being trivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or diſcarded, thoſe of others to their unexerciſed apprehenſions appear ſtrange and difficult: Hence Curioſity (the idle mans Mephoſtophllus) poſts through the air to catch intelligence, and adviſo's upon the ſeveral emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, being ſure to meet ſome looſe diſpatches, out of what quarter ſoever the wind does but breath. Theſe ſtill conjure up new perplexities, freſh and fantaſtique conjectures, which firſt creep forth in whiſpers and night diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, then more boldly come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and ſtand the cenſures of their full Burnt-to-water Conventions, or higher Club-Aſſemblies; if in private affairs, they are inſolent and diſguſtful; if on publick, their interpolate Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and wildly wiſe Apothegms eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104697:21"/>where bring in growing diſcontents and murmurings: not without a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle indeed can it be expected, any thing ſhould pleaſe and ſatisfie them abroad, who never knew the Art to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent within, and at home. But if this ubiquitary medling ſeem to abſolve theſe kind of perſons from Idleneſs, and they will hence be thought as active in the Intelligencies of the ſpheres, and the only they that keep all in motion; Thoſe that know what harmony is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd to a motion regular, and how ſure a ſtop the leaſt duſt and check will cauſe in a fine contrived piece of work, will wiſh them quiet, and unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted reſt, may but the buſineſſe of the ſober and induſtrious part of mankind be removed out of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Orb. And as to our increaſe in Riches, when every hand and brain promote and incourage a proſperous diligence; None are found ſo idle as to queſtion it, though ſo d ſobliging and unworthy of their native Country, as to ſtigmatize and empoveriſh it with <pb n="25" facs="tcp:104697:21"/>their ſloth. For ſenſible will be the decays of that body, from which you ſubſtract nouriſhment and exerciſe; the latter whereof mends all the defaults of the former, ſtirrs up a kindly warmth, facilitates digeſtion, diſcuſſes excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious humors, purifies and exhili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the depreſſed ſpirits. But no more need be added on this tenacious ſubject, than that if your years and quality could get above the droſs and dregs of idleneſſe, ſo as to lay out your ſelves vigilantly in the ſervice your Generation calls you unto, and may expect of you, if Idleneſſe be exploded; We ſhall have leſſe news and more money ſtirring.</p>
               <p>Having beheld the Soul under this cloſe and obſcure incubation; Let us view the brood hatched by ignorance and Folly: and the earlieſt we meet up, is</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104697:22"/>
               <head>PRIDE,</head>
               <p>Breaking thorough the thick ſhel; which, haſting to be the firſt diſplaying its gay Plumes abroad, forgets how much of its nakedneſſe is expoſed, and that it ows all its pomp to a borrowed Gawdineſs, Man enters the world bare and unarm'd, all other creatures growing into their furrs, ſhels, barks, down-quilts and ſcaly Coats of Mail; each of which has as much of defenſe as ornament: Yet none of theſe but willingly bequeath their ſpoyls, to rob man of his poor Pride, who cannot ſo much as ſhrowd himſelf from the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the air but in ſome of their live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Yet who but computes the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery which curious invention has ſpun us out of all the parts of the inferiour creation; ſome from its very bowels as fine drawn as the web of <hi>Arachne,</hi> the loom-work of the Brain, and the very net of love it ſelf; and conſiders withall how many operoſe preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:104697:22"/>various interweavings and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of diff'ring elements meet in the meaneſt ſhreds of our Wardrobe; muſt neceſſarily inſer that the whole ſtudies of man were to beguile the Creatures of their deſigne; as if he ſcorn'd to be indebted to them, for what they can never diſtinguiſh again, to have been their old caſt cloaths; Or as if he intended in his very attire (not contented with the covering of any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Animal) to ſtitch together another Epitome of the Creation for his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide alſo; and, in the far diſtant growth of his gorgeous apparel, would array himſelf daily with a new map of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy.</p>
               <p>But all this pageantry covers not the miſerable inſide, but like the ragged embroidery of a Beggars patches, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the wretched poverty within; the poor mind neither knowing it ſelf, nor any thing beſide it ſelf, from either of which it would learn humility. But Pride is the ſpawn of Idleneſſe, and the foam of Ignorance: Where ever
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104697:23"/>you meet her, give her rather your hat than your tongue; for it is unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you ſhould reverence her in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dialect than that ſhe wears, and you will otherwiſe run the hazard of being underſtood. Is it not a ſplene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic divertiſement to behold two Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants as formally rigged forth, as <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Amſterdam,</hi> or <hi>Venice</hi> can equip them, attaquing each other with a full bearing up to the ſalute, ſometime vei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down every inch of their ſails, ſtreaming out all their looſe colours, and pendents, and ſuddainly cloſing with whole Broadſides of embraces? while not a word attends the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, (which is like the great <hi>CZars</hi> dump repreſentative of a ſage Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil) and they come off perhaps with a furled cuff, a ſilken rope ſlack'd, or a curle unpitch'd (I mean ungumm'd, or ungreas'd) This you may call the School of Antiques, a very variation of Poſtures, a Tryal of Agility, and ſuch a mute compariſon of empty Noddles, as we make of Bottles by <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104697:23"/>oft and quick ſhaking them.</p>
               <p>And this is the ſtately outſide and high-raiz'd Front of Pride: which content your ſelf to have thus ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeen, if you will not reſt here but enter further, look for no recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or refreſhment within, there are no commodious rooms contriv'd to that intent; for this is a pile wholly loftyfied into Garrets, and they either empty or the Frippery of all Traſh and Lumber: but here moſt of the world chuſe to dwell, as where they can beſt overlook themſelves, as well as their vicinage.</p>
               <p>I may give Pride the Title (or ſhe will take it) of Heir apparent in the maſculine, to the greateſt portion of their Time and Care. With the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſex let her be advanc'd for their Mirrour, that which flatters them even out of themſelves into a kind of fond Apotheoſis: You muſt no longer read there fleſh and bloud no, the eyes, the lips and breath, are the very portals of the radiant <hi>Apollo,</hi> the heavenly bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104697:24"/>of <hi>Aurora,</hi> and the fragrant incenſe that muſt appeaſe ſome ſuch Deity. Thus Youth and Beauty in either Sex, kindled by a conſtant reflexion of its own beams, and having no other fair object to attract it powerfully and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, glows with a burning ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complacency, till a rapid Zeale of Pride ſnatch the conceits of themſelves beyond the terms of mortality, and they deem they ſenſibly change regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſtep into a deifying naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation, ſo that you may no more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a converſe with them that ſavors of humanity: all the reſt of mankind are to be treated by them as their vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals and creatures, and their very words muſt be thought to ſound more then man. And that they may command this devotion and maintain a juſt ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they appear not without the pomp and ſplendor which are worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Images of Saints and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhrines and altars, that do not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige vulgar veneration, unleſs em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhed with ſumptuous ornaments,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104697:24"/>and glittering oblations: In ſuch a mantle of Gold they will imitate Jove, and conceive they have no imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which theſe ductile leaves do not gloriouſly hide and heal.</p>
               <p>Thus Pride ſacrificeth to her ſelf, not only with the groſſer material trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and riches imploy'd in her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but with the refined odors that riſe from her own perſumed delights with her ſelf, and the high conveiv'd pleaſure in her own felicities. But can the rough buſh of a quick-ſet haire fence off all frigidity from the Brain, and ſhelter the tender <hi>Pia mater</hi> from ſcratches? Do's a beſpangled Veſt caſt a greater heat and blaze on the hearth of the Breaſt? To what then, ſerve the exquiſite ſtudy and profuſions la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd out on our dreſſing? ſome <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let de Chambre,</hi> Player or Common woman, ſhall ſurpaſs your bravery when you have born the patience of the niceſt accoutrement. Believe it, the Art you beſtow and Value you ſet upon your dreſs and habit, lay more <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104697:25"/>open the uglineſſe, poverty and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your Soul, and ſhew that firſt needed <hi>fucus</hi> and Emplaiſters to pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate your inward ſores and defects.</p>
               <p>But our Otioſo's here plead the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable morality, and that they are hound to the ſtricteſt obſervances of the Faſhion; than which word none can breath more infection, nothing appear in a better mode and more ſure to captivate and deſtroy us: As what allows us neither conſtancy in our preſent fluctuancie's, nor any fair calculation of hopes for futurity, if it muſt be omnipotent then alſo: It can introduce the moſt fanatique Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſes of our ſelves, and patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize all the Caprichio's of the famous Shrew-Tamer. To inſtance but in one aſſimilative attraction in its very Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillaries, no leſs remarkable than that which is perfective of nature: Obſerve how faſhion has prevail'd againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Perruque all complexions with the faireſt hair; where many muſt be wholly drown'd, as the <hi>Portuguez, <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104697:25"/>Amorettaes</hi> at <hi>Goa</hi> their <hi>Negro</hi> women, whom they dreſſe up all in white, to make up their admired Beauty of a Fly in milk. But as this ſhades and deſtroys the diſtinctions and native fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of each face, it may unluckily be brought to confound all diſtinctions of birth too, by ſuppoſing thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny indiſcriminated (not to ſay unknown) Heads to have had but one common Parent; At leaſt that this connatural ſimilitude links them all under the ſame Hereditary Craſineſs of the Brain.</p>
               <p>How predominantly ſucceſsful is this Supreme Legiſlative Faſhion? Laws, Examples, Rewards, Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cannot enforce an Uniformity in any other Medium; while ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone tranſlates and alters the world at pleaſure, making it ſolicitous to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey her, deriving her Formulaires and ſcanty Praeſcripts to it, with the ſame Authority the <hi>Medes</hi> and
<hi>Parthians</hi> ſealed up their Laws, and that alone in that theſe are moſt alterable.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:104697:26"/>
               <p>But I am not at leaſure to give lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger attendance on Pride, who I doubt will diſdain to have its meaſures alſo taken by a countrey hand: Without a Complement I aſſure her, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire her inconceivable pleaſure and ſelf opinion on which ſhe lives; as much as I ſhould have done <hi>Regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montanus</hi> his Fly, if he could have ſhut up life as well as motion in ſo narrow room. For to ſee a Gallant flutter and buzze, with no other wings than his Taylor has imp'd on, to ſtrut like a dancing Mr. to ſpeak by determined and unaccountable motions and ſprings, and nothing to be ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant without a multi-ſcrewing body; can I look upon him to be other than a fine articulate Engine, a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit of Man, and the larger ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of ſome Puzzionello? And thus taken in pieces you ſee the ſtuffing and crutches, Pride ſwells and ſtalks on. But what eſteem wiſe and ſober men ballaſt themſelves with, you can take from the true knowledge and ſtudy <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104697:26"/>of your ſelves only, to make your own ſufficient inſtruction and ſupport: Where you will ſoon learn the enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of the mind to be the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect accompliſhing of the man; which, by its fairer acceſſions of virtue and wiſedome, debaſeth the inferior gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications and mistaken opinions of its own Dignity; to keep it ſelf up with an equal moderation, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity too great to ſtoop to any Vice; eſpecially the depravations of Pride, in the effeminacies I have branded of thoſe perſons, whoſe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt attainments are the dear purchaſe, moſt accurate oſtentation, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Vanity of their Attire.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Hero,</hi> who is a Denizon of the Univerſe, no where deveſts himſelf of his invariable habit of Virtue; which, as the richeſt, warmeſt, eaſieſt, and immaculate, can never be worn out of Faſhion.</p>
               <p>That Pride, which grows out of pregnant faculties and ample improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Time and Parts, is ſo far <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104697:27"/>from falling under our cenſure here, that we may rather applaud and promote it; that it may retain its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and juſt contempt of theſe inſignificant Poppets and Mormoes; whoſe ſouls, bodies, and cloaths ſeem to be but one Compoſition; and as if they were all taken up at the ſame ſhop and artificially bombaſted and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted to ſuſtain a burthen of wealth, and fairly turn it ſelf to all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of brutiſh ſenſuality. Of this nobler and more ſubſtantial baſis of Pride let this though be here ſaid, and conſidered with all the weight of ſeriouſneſſe: That their brave ſpirits will bear an higher flight, and there is yet above them a pleaſure as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory and durable, as this of their high-born Pride is certainly moſt je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>june, and no leſs low and tranſient.</p>
               <p>But the Epicure muſt be ſerv'd in the next place to Pride: and</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:104697:27"/>
               <head>INTEMPERANCE,</head>
               <p>Is uſually willing to yield unto her precedence, but on good proviſion to be made for its Appetite immediately to ſucceed. For it well reliſheth the Genius of the Marceſe in their recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Meſſire, and this Honorific Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles return, in diſcovering to them the rate preparation of the leaf of a Swine. So low a rate has been ſet upon the Man, ſince the faireſt part of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter is, that he eats and drinks well, and knows good food, nothing better. As if the ſoul of the Glutton were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon him only to be a Catereſſe to his carcaſſe, and ſee the larder of the ſtomach be not unfurniſht: Nay, it often has no higher office than of a Cook, and feaſts it ſelf with the skill to provoke, as well as allay Hunger and Thirſt. What <hi>Adepti</hi> are thoſe admired to be, who can diſcourſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly on a ſtudied diſh, can anoto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize it dextrouſly, ſhew you what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <pb n="38" facs="tcp:104697:28"/>qualities meet in its temperament, give you all the criticiſms, and ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize the various Guſtoes of meats and liquors? To have the preſence of ſuch a Vertuoſo is the beſt countenance you can give your Treat, and your Friend; you may be ſure in his company you ſupp'd in <hi>Apollo:</hi> Such a mans palat and Face (for there you may taſt his aſſay) are as cautiouſly obſerv'd by the whole Table, as if they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his preſcriptions for diet; and as neceſſary as the previous infuſion of the Unicorns horn to the patient Herd. His frown is as fatal to the Cook as the Judges on the Bench, and ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all he ſends up worſe than at the rack. This man needs not
<hi>Philoxenus</hi> his wiſh, for whatſoever is born down the ſwallow of any at the board, I may ſay, he has the pleaſure of its guſt; for it becomes Manna to all the Gueſts by yielding the taſt he put upon it, and he may eaſily be underſtood to have the volupe of his Palat extended in all theirs.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104697:28"/>
               <p>Seems not this to be the inſtinct of a gallant and acute ſoul? is not this a Guſto raiſed and fitted alone for
<hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſia</hi> and <hi>Nepenthe?</hi> Yes certainly. And you may believe ſuch choice Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ands will yield a concoction of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that cannot but colonize the brain with moſt defaecate and noble Conceptions. For they farſe themſelves with the moſt exquiſite delicacies, as if neither their bodies were caſt in the mould of Earth, nor their regalioes but the various-form'd figures of the duſt they raiſe, nor the ſpirits from them other than the brood which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Animals generate out of the graſs we trample on. But in truth do they not by their exceſs and high feeding oppreſs the brain, and ſuffocate its o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations with fuliginous ſteams from the kitchin, obſtructing the fine chanels and pipes, which ſhould tranſmit the finer and nimble ſpirits to all their ſtages, and for all their admirable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatches and functions; while the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundancy of dull pituitous moiſture <pb n="40" facs="tcp:104697:29"/>unſtrings, and intercepts their vigorous tenſion, and ſenſation?</p>
               <p>No, they are phlegmatic ſouls who think a load of dainties enrich this ſoil with any other product than what we caſt out, and ſpread upon the common. The mind is that dry and clear light, maintain'd in its Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gils by an even, conſtant, and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate confluence of pure and innocent Spirits: You drown it by powring in too much (though never ſo rich) Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor; if you impregnate its oyl with too fat and droſſy a Sulphur, it ſends forth as noyſom ſtenches as <hi>Vulcan's</hi> Cave, and is orecaſt with an encir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cling ſhadow: if you fret it with acid and ſaline particles, how diſturbed is its flame and offenſive with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual crackling exploſions of thoſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie bodies? While the poor ſoul ſtarves for want of its mean and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repaſt: The pamper'd body too, ſurcharg'd with crudities, or an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown ſtock of fleſh, becomes its own unweildy impediment (needing <pb n="41" facs="tcp:104697:29"/>ſome Engine, like the Chariot the
<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> annex to their ſheep, to bear up thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> monſtrous train of Tail) &amp; not ſeldome is it an Hoſpital of diſeaſes, and its own Houſe of correction too.</p>
               <p>Into an unſhapen bulk have we ſeen many extended, whoſe parts are as uſeleſs to them as if growing in another Countrey; like the unviſited rooms of ſome great Houſes (ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the care and concern of the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) that Vermin have come to neſtle and burrough in the wide tenements of their Fleſh. And truly they muſt of neceſſity devize ſome proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable accretion and enlargement of their Soul, if they would have all their apartiments and needleſs ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructures well tenanted and kept in conſtant repair. But the direct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is their ruine; for they appear with ſo little of the preſence of a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit animating them, that what they have of life is like that to be ſeen on the bodies of Witches in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies; where the ſoul is withdrawn <pb n="42" facs="tcp:104697:30"/>into the moſt cloſe and ſilent receſs, (the ſtate of the voluptuous
<hi>Egyptian Calyphs</hi> of old) while they dawb up the pores and outward chinks, to make the retiring room more dark and warm, and guard the paſſes againſt foreign invaſions. The ſoul is in ſo little caſe in theſe additional out-jet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and looſer edifices; that immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a larger compaſs of ground, it is but more labyrinthally and ſecurely impriſoned. So ſome number of the world are buried under the curſe of their much building, and not a few maſters famiſh'd to keep their beaſts luſty: by the inverted divine admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to fortifie the inward man upon the ruines of the outward.</p>
               <p>But our <hi>Apitii</hi> ſcorn to have their enjoyments ſtreightned, though more ſafely enſconced; they muſt every day rove abroad to fetch in ſacrifices to their <hi>Oeſophagus,</hi> and lowdly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lennize the feſtivals of <hi>Comus,</hi> crown'd with freſh chaplets of Ivy and Myrtles: offering up the moſt delicious morſels
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104697:30"/>the world has in ſtore, in their Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinarian Targets of <hi>Minerva;</hi> as if ſhe were here to be again born out of the variety of far-fetch'd brains, and Tongues: with no leſs libations of the
<hi>Falernian</hi> grape, in their lofty ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying <hi>Tricongio</hi> Goblets. By the full draughts they quaff off in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt bloud of the Vine you would gueſs they deſigned to imitate <hi>Jove</hi> and
<hi>Mercury,</hi> and having fil'd a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of an whole Oxe hide (once the Continent of a City) with this caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Liquor, would with equal ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and authority, conſtellate it into an Aethereal Urinal. Or if
<hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> may not owe his riſe from ſo low ſprings, you would conceive they had new caſt themſelves into humane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lembicks, from whom nothing leſs then Spirits of Wines ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted; and from the ſame copious and rich luxury of meats they prey upon, that ſome Chymiſt had dearly purchas'd their more terrene excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, out of them to exalt his Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental <pb n="44" facs="tcp:104697:31"/>cidental zibeth. So laboriouſly does Gluttony plough up land and ſeas; and prohibit the free and open refuges of the enſna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Air; to ſerve up that plenty to our ſurfeited Tables, which is in its ſecond courſe muſt be exonera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the Eſquiline port. This and the Vrinary evacuate thoſe Oceans of voluptuouſneſſe, and mountains of wealth, out of which you cannot on the neareſt reſearch derive and gain one leaſt grain of Profit, or the ſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt drop of remaining pleaſure. There in corruption they all periſh; where man himſelf muſt at laſt alight from his Journey, to caſt up the total of his expenſes, in the ſhort concluſion of Vanity and Vexation.</p>
               <p>We need no more admire the cup of <hi>Circe,</hi> and the fictitious mutatious Poets have licenced: they relate men turn'd into ordinarily known Beaſts: but we every day ſee a new ſpecies of brutes, as cruel as monſtrous, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred in our luxuries; which were I to digeſt into one collection, you <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104697:31"/>would ſee a ſtranger Pyramid and larger than great Abbeſs erected in his Capital City of <hi>Perſia;</hi> you might alſo phanſie every diſh, and glaſs of wine, productive of a different kind of Animals. But what rubricks the nefariouſneſs of our Times, is to be drawn from drunkenneſs, which draws more ſwords and blood of our Nation in one year, than any one bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail ſpends in the ſame compaſs of time; The ſanguine quarrels of our Compotations, like the famous ſet of Teeth, whence ſo many armed Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions grew, divide the Bravoes, and their intereſts, into new and ſober conteſts, and ſpring up into a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like harveſt of factions and Duels. For we continually ſee theſe intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancies creating more Enemies, than good nature (to which none more pretend) can make Friends, and the ſtrongeſt fidelity ſhipwrackt and ſplit in a ſmall glaſſe of wine drank or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:104697:32"/>
               <p>But beſide this dangerous Service, wherein a man ventures his life as cheaply and commonly, as a poor Souldier that for ſix-pence the day ſtands in the breach, and tempts every ſhot; there is a ſecret poiſon envenoms this Good-fellowſhip, a ſting that makes a breach in a mans boſom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his skill ever to compoſe, and reconcile with a perfect cure. Wine for the moſt part eludes the Guards every man ought to have upon his own breaſt, and breaks open the locks of all his Conclave and Cabinet Secrets: He is then like a Veſſel full of Leaks, and the Liquor waſheth all before it: if he have any infirmity of mind or latent Vice, this empties and diſgorgeth all: he ſhall need no other Indictment than his own treacherous evidence, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent folly; which the moſt ſober of his proteſts and retractations ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver expunge. Should another be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate to the confident truſt and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome One repoſes in his deareſt Friend, to whom he emboſomes his <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104697:32"/>whole-ſelf; ſhould he break in upon the free Careſſes and Amours of the Conjugal Bed, about which the Night has drawn a ſecond and modeſt Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; ſhould he hear his open Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to Heaven of all his baſeneſs, and and unworthy abuſe of infinite conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentions: As ſoon as this perſon who thought himſelf in the dark ſhall find himſelf expoſed and betrayed, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine but his indignation will be all thought too little to torment him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone, without regard of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Traitor. And I am confident, were Windows thus made into our hearts and actions, Man would ſo far hate converſe, as rather to ſeek the moſt ſolitary and diſmal Wilderneſs; Nay, knowing his own miſery by the view he would not have had of it, but from others prying examinations, He would even flie his own ſhadow, and ſtudy how he might run from and avoyd himſelf, as the only derided and inſulted on by all the reſt of the world.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:104697:33"/>
               <p>The more noted diſguiſes Ebriety put's upon men; with the detriment, mind, Body, and Eſtate ſuffer by the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revocable lapſes of them all: The moſt ſottiſh of thoſe, who moſt ſtudy to amuſe their own heavy hours, thoughts, and company with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment and fallacy of Wine, yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not meaſure it out, but with the many obſervations from their own acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance they miſs at the Club, and rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their former jovialties toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I therefore induſtriouſly diſmiſs them, having but inſinuated the height of Paſſion it inflames, and ſometimes feeds with blood, and the life of Amity it ſelf; with that exulcerate feebleneſs of reaſon, which by an impotent teneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus betrays the infirmities of thoſe, we almoſt Idoliz'd, to ſcorn and hatred.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who indulge Gluttonous vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity fare no better, by exchanging ſanity of mind and Body for the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of both; the former in many, ſcarce owning the preſervative quality of being a living pickle to the latter. <pb n="49" facs="tcp:104697:33"/>Not <hi>Cleopatra's</hi> diſſolv'd Union, the Spicery of <hi>Arabia,</hi> with the genuine Balſam and skil of the
<hi>Egyptian</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balmers, can long keep thoſe bowels from putrefaction, which we ſo ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly pamper: Theſe being the very firſt conceive it, on the diſſociation of ſoul and body. Methinks thoſe very Fingers with which we carry our dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to our Palate, that with our Rings bear the Sepulchral heads of ſome of our former familiarity, ſhould indigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate to us a Lecture of our own mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and tell us, we all the while feed our animated <hi>Sarcophagi.</hi> I ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine whether Fire or Earth be the moſt faithful Heirs, Aſſigns, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitories of our Reliques; for perhaps every Tomb may encloſe in it a ſelf-ſubſiſtent lamp, as the Heart alive en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys it's vital flame, and the Spirits render the whole body luminous, as well as pervious, till Death breaks open, and let's out the light. But I am ſure our Glutton gormandizes, as if he would make his Friends their laſt <pb n="50" facs="tcp:104697:34"/>Treat of his own Corps; and, that in which has liv'd to devoure ſo many Thanks giving meals, ſerve them up a bill of Fare equal to the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Yorks</hi> Inaugura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Feaſt; and with the ſame cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie inſtal himſelf in the kind graves and Monuments of his laſt Officious Friends ſurviving Stomachs.</p>
               <p>From the good chear and wine, that has diſpos'd our Gallant to the embrace of any near hovering and baſer Form, we moſt uſually trace him to the lap of his <hi>Venus:</hi> the little bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie <hi>Cupids</hi> of</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LUST</head>
               <p>Dancing about in the looſe Air, inſtantly gliding into poſſeſſion of his mind; where all the weak chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Virtue and ſobriety are waſht out, to make a Table fair enough to render any Vice more legible that ſhall be firſt impreſſ'd in it. The Cittadel of the Heart thus unmann'd, <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104697:34"/>is eaſily ſurpriz'd and garriſon'd with a miſerable woman; Who never thinks the Victory abſolute and ſecure till ſhe have demoliſht all the Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his reaſon and modeſty, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph'd over his cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iv'd tame paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and raiſed in it a Moſque to the blind God of Love. Here you ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Cytherea</hi> born out of the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pumations of our Seas of Wine, with this only difference, ſhe is not naked, but appears more formidably arm'd to conquer man than
<hi>Jove</hi> and <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> with their Thunder and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Upon this Ocean you may cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fear the incurſions of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Rover, whom I may call a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of warr (with no greater ſolae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm than that, which gives the femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine gender in ordinary diſcourſe of a man of War) dreſt only with ſlight tackling, and wary concealments drawn over her ſhot, to amuſe you; or make a more ſpeedy chace after you when flying from her: Here lading is not worth reprizal whatever damage ſhe <pb n="52" facs="tcp:104697:35"/>had done you: Her veſſel ſuffers not by ſtorms or repeated wrecks; nor can you any way direct a ſhot to ſink it; ſhe only ſuffers by Fire, and carrying ſo prodigious ſtore of Ammunition is to be blown up not boarded.</p>
               <p>Let me eſſay to give you ſome ſuch Character of
<hi>Venus,</hi> (if any be to be taken of her, pozing us with her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tean diſguizes, not perfections) and directions in your obnoxiouſneſs, by which you may avoid the dangerous incantations of theſe Syrens. That which firſt betrays us is the ſuppoſed Beauty we drink greedily in at our ſtartled eies, if not join'd with the heats of ſome too kind and cloſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes: and how deſperate madneſs is it, when the heart is the Mine of ſo combuſtible Luſt, to ſuffer the looſe <hi>globuli</hi> of powder catch fire at the eies and lips, which with the twinkling of an eye ſpring the incendiary Train to the magazine of its Wildfire? But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we are here fairly cheated in our purſuits and reveries to ſingle beauty;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:104697:35"/>We admire that for Orient, ſweet, and perfectly ſymmetriz'd, which is but the tincture and odor ſhe borrows every morning from the Cloſet, and the Tailors ingenious farcings: For when ſhe is dreſt, ſo little a part ſhe is then of her ſelf, as is the ſmall Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of the <hi>Lauretan</hi> Lady, under the great and rich cover they have cloath'd it withall: and indeed a Woman un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt to her ſelf dreſt, is like a Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to a Palace; Dreſſing is a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Art of Architecture, and the extraordinary niceneſs and expenſes thereof the Curſe and diſeaſe of too much Riches.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing a face as lovely as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you ador'd in a dream, or can phancy without the help of one; This complexion is but vaniſhing and skin deep. Sickneſs, Grief, or Age make as heavy devaſtations on it, as the barbarous Tartars can doe, in their inroads to a flouriſhing Country: Raiſe up but the skarfe skin which covers this fine mould, and you never <pb n="54" facs="tcp:104697:36"/>beheld a more ruefull object: Or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it as the admired frontiſpiece of an excellent Fabrick, and but conſider what is done within, how theſe fair embelliſhments are but neat contriv'd emunctories to the Brain; and you muſt think of ſomething loathſome alſo. 'Tis your own phancy feaſts it ſelf with the perfections it has created to worſhip; So prompt and cunning it is to cook up a known and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entertainment, into new and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious blandiſhments. But if you are not to be out of conceit with the face, conſider what manner of deformed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant inſpirits this Beauty; and that a monſtrous ſoul in an illuſtrious caſe, needs your compaſſion on the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency which is greater than that <hi>Galba</hi> paid rent for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nay it requires your utmoſt vigilancy too: for this Creature feeds on poyſons, and kills with her looks and breath. For to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all muſt be fair within, becauſe of this ſpecious ſuperficies, and that a ſweet countenance neceſſarily dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifies <pb n="55" facs="tcp:104697:36"/>and clarifies the ſoul; is to place the Lanthorn of <hi>Judas,</hi> and adore it among ſacred Reliques; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it lighted the Traitor to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of our Bleſſed Saviour. If that ſex, as virtuous as beautiful, be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical, 'tis more diabolical by its Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</p>
               <p>It is an unparallel'd ſlavery to bow your affections to the imperiouſneſs of ſuch a lewd ſoul, who requires the quite contrary experiment of ſervitude, to that the beſtial Duke of <hi>Oſſuna</hi> fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his naked Barber into: for ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects as eaſie command of your paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as her skill has perfected hers into by the art of obeying wholly her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidinous appetite. What miſery muſt it be to be enthrall'd to a ſort of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Animals than mankind, of whom I may almoſt virifie the Turkiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; that ſuch as theſe have loſt their ſoul?
<hi>Tacitus</hi> himſelf aphorizeth no leſs in his ſhort and poynant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion with <hi>Meſſalina.</hi> Could you ſee the inſide of this ſtrange Woman, <pb n="56" facs="tcp:104697:37"/>you would find it altogether a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of outſides; an exchange of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring habits, looks, and phraſes ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to every circumſtance of diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Sometime ſhe is as inacceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as <hi>Valentia,</hi> to which no other then a narrow bridge permits approach and all ſeems to be horrid Alps about it, rocks frozen harder and colder with froſt and ſnow; and none but an <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal</hi> would hope to break thorough them. Anon, like the Town <hi>Plura</hi> on a ſuddain fall of a rock ſubverted, and nothing to be ſeen of it but a dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lake.</p>
               <p>Such an one indeed is a common ſewer of Luſt, and Druggs. For the latter like the Hoſpital near the Church-yard of magnificent St.
<hi>Peters</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> cannot lay farr off: and 'tis well if ſhe have not the quick dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion alſo of that Earth, once part of Holy ground. I am ſure you know not what dangers and evils you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on. Inconſtancy, Impetuoſity, Fallaciouſneſs are the compoſition of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104697:37"/>their Love, Luſt the informant. Scarce ever do any reaſſume chaſtity, who have once depos'd it. For immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty ſtraight enthrones a Plebeian u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping community, that attaint the nobleſt ſpirits which uſe to bluſh at Baſeneſs, and by its hatred of all ſence of Honor puts all that is honeſt and generous out of countenance. Then you will too late groan under the Tyranny and fatigues which mind and body are involv'd in, when you find your ſelf both as far from the ſatisfaction and happineſs you ſigh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as in that hour you firſt became her Votary; and no nearer liberty then the Galley-ſlave, who expects Death alone to unchain him from the Oar. For like the labors of <hi>Hercules</hi> ſome new exploit will ſtill be conjur'd up to deſtroy or enſure your courage and obſequiouſneſs, and like him you will endure a dying life, in thoſe flames Love, and Jealouſie can never make too hot for their Purgatory.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:104697:38"/>
               <p>Yet at the no eaſie rates of a <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican Limbus,</hi> our Age will buy the pleaſure of its Luſt. Neither the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment of their hopes, vaſſalage of their paſſions, nor Penances (At the price whereof they would renounce Heaven it ſelf) can make theſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac's temperate. And indeed they ſeem to be under an high diſtemper of mind and body; the ſolicitude, inſaciety, viciſſitude of violent affections, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, are ſymptoms of that: the pale face, vibrated eies, inequal pulſe, and their waking <hi>Coma</hi> ſhew this to be under an acute feaver, which all their long ſighs cannot haſten in breath enough to cool.</p>
               <p>But if you obtain the utmoſt fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itions of your Amours, if you fear no Rival, if your joynt affections be emboſom'd in one common breaſt, and you know not how to expreſs or entertain a more full indulgency of Love; All the hiſtory hereof does o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly confeſs this your happineſs, to be empty, ſhallow, and miſerable: For <pb n="59" facs="tcp:104697:38"/>the moſt pathetic Language of your melting affections can ſpeak or ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie no more than bare commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or bold wiſhes over your Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; wherein you rather pity and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail one another in the ſhort capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Love, than take or give any perfect proof or content in it: While your greateſt efforts of paſſion doe but inſtruct the mind in its tremulous flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuancies, that it is at the wrong point of the Magnet; and only condole over its affections to be ſo fruſtrated of their reſt, and permanent ſatisfaction. For the acqueſt then of no more; Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you ſtake the All of your ſelf, whatever that can amount to, for the hectic feaver of a conſuming, incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, fugacious, phantaſtic brutiſh pleaſure, which concludes, without extorted acknowledgment, that you are deluded, and infinitely ſhort of that good, the Soul would quietly reſt in, without forming ſo much as one thought to uncenter it ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:104697:39"/>
               <p>None that finds Opinion the Empreſs of the world, but obſerves Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to be the ladders by which it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended: Paſſions which ſupplant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to whom they were given in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and ſervice, and gain the intire government of our wils. So does luſt aſſign it ſelf to its enſnaring object, That it uſes to prefer it abundantly, before the particular content, which every individual enjoys of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors goodneſs, to reckon himſelf ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractedly happy in: (had not every one ſuch an innate principle, emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and envy would continually torture the Soul, and we ſhould wiſh to be any thing but what we are) now an unlawful Love cancels this beatifying apprehenſion, and connatural emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of delight, which is ſuckt from out of it ſelf alone; and impoſes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Standard of your joy. What you love you live; Your paſſion, ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all other concerns, erects a Court of Requeſts, out of which nothing is to be transacted, and the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104697:39"/>and deſign of living ſhall be to love: And that love, adoreing its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſo tranſportedly, never ceaſeth to conſigne it ſelf over by its own exina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition; to become and be transform'd into what it loves. I could hence philoſophize nicely on the cauſe of the diſtinct formation of either Sex, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the receiv'd Tradition, that the predominant virtue determines the conception into its own ſimilitude: which would ſolve divers ſubtleties, but it is excentric. From this diſcourſe you have this ſad conſequence, that the object poſſeſſing and impaſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting you, will certainly infuſe into you all thoſe vitious defects her degenerate mind has contracted, and you yield up your own integrity to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by her monſtrous depravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Thus much more you ſee you ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of your ſelf for ſo remarkable an infatuation; and if you will add unto it the diuturnity, and (I had almoſt ſaid) impoſſibility of vindicating your <pb n="62" facs="tcp:104697:40"/>ſelf from this Bondage; You have ſound out a State of direful miſery, ineluctable and deplorable ſadneſs. For Love though it be ſlowly and late aſcendent, ſeldome ſetts, but with our ſelves deſcending into ſhades and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion. 'Tis not the firſt living, but of the laſt dying emotions of the ſoul: You ſee it will ſtrive under all the infirmities of old Age, to render it as ridiculous as inſufficient. You cannot when you pleaſe divorce it your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted boſom: it wakes with you, and laies down beſide you; and when you court ſome ſoft repoſe and ſilence, it breaks in upon you withal the noiſe tumult and lancination of diſtracted paſſions, holding your eies open to its raviſhments, though you behold no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therein but your own ſuffrings. So have I ſeen a poor captive Bird, when attempting a free and open flight, rudely checkt with the ſhort twine, and after a ſmall hovering and fluttering reſiſtance in the affected air, fall breathleſs groveling on the earth. <pb n="63" facs="tcp:104697:40"/>On the folly of poor ſtupid man, that, as much as it abhorrs the very ſhadow of reſtraint and fetters, which are of anothers impoſing, yet ſtudies to build himſelf a Labyrinth, and thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not ſecure of his liberty; till he have contriv'd how ingeniouſly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carcerate his freeborn affections! Thus thoſe who dreaded the Roman yoak, by the ſame methods of Fear ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Nation to their voracious Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, only having the election how to periſh.</p>
               <p>Should I after ſome dark and rough draughts delineating your miſery, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to heighten the few faint appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of your imagined felicity and light titillations of ſence; and fill it up with the many deep ſhadows, and ſtrong grounded horrors which the paſſions draw upon amorous Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants: You would think it the very picture of that Carcaſe which had been martyr'd in Venereal fires, and was conſerv'd as a ſpecific againſt Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery. Or that you ſaw ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal <pb n="64" facs="tcp:104697:41"/>night-piece, on which one looſe touch of the Pencil had thinn'd the air, but ſo as if it had but with a thought only follow'd the ſwift flight of an Angel thorough it. So tranſient is the extaſie of your delight and pleaſure, over the black viſions of Luſt.</p>
               <p>Can I ſay more to prejudicate and arm you when your Soul will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger'd by this aſſaſſination, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what circumventions will ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time be prevalent, which theſe Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to our nature would wholly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare you in; and that all I can ſay will be little enough to inſtruct your innocence, and I fear much too weak to reſcue it from a ſurprize, much more out of the faſtneſſes of a ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuſtomed and Familiar Vice? Theſe kind of Creatures therefore the Predatory ſpirits upon the life of man we have not a word in all the vocabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary of evills bad enough to ſignifie their hideous Turpitude, unleſs I could pliancy it ſo completed, that they had nothing more to add to make it <pb n="65" facs="tcp:104697:41"/>more Fatal to us. Put the malice of theſe ſorcereſſes is ſo fruitful of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, that we are only happy that the Fount of Goodneſs is inexhauſtible, when we ſee all degrees of miſery diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeminated out of their circulating <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora</hi>'s Box. You cannot comprehend the myſtery of the ſacramental Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation they have made of themſelves in their Vow of Proſtitution: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they devote themſelves to corrupt and debauch Man from his Integrity and felicity: So difficult will it be to prognoſticate what villanies will not be broached by them, to poyſon the world with a worſe plague than that from <hi>Naples.</hi> Shew me that ſincerity Grandieur, Sapience that has eſcap'd their pernicious attempts: Shew me the greateſt combination of nefariouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs has but been meditated, and I will more than exemplifie it in ſome notorious impudence, or profligate treachery of a woman. Our bleſſed Lord and Saviour among all tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, permitted not this of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:104697:42"/>ſo much as to be levell'd againſt him; ſo immaculate Virtue could no more admit a conflict with this impurity, than the Sun it ſelf can be ſuppoſ'd aſſaulted with midnight. And we know it the Guardian, as well as honour of Innocence to be free from all ſuſpicion and darings of a very tempting vice. But the firſt, beſt, ſtrongeſt, greateſt and wiſeſt of meer men, ſpeak their diminution in all theſe, by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy connexion to theſe indeclinable particles of Levity. They are indeed themſelves the nullity of all words: Nothing they ſpeak is more ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al than their very looks, which every breath of yours, and (what is out of all compaſſe more variable) their own deſultory phanſy alters often in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>I am angry with my invention to be ſo jaded in ſo fowl a Road, every progreſſion is more ſqualid and miry to me, yet I want dirt enough to caſt upon theſe ſeeming <hi>Viae Lacteae.</hi> Who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rubb'd on ſo exquiſite a dealbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <pb n="67" facs="tcp:104697:42"/>that my very Ink looſeth its blacks upon them. Neither think me provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked or in paſſion beyond the Antipathy every good Soul has to Hypocriſie. Believe me then, theſe are the grand Favorites of Hell, or the apteſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<hi>Lucifer</hi> ever ſchool'd, that are ſo eaſily and naturally accommodated to that Art, that what we ſay of common Lyars own belief, that to them warrants at laſt their often queſtioned, and therefore more cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous Fictions, we may here apply, That ſo induſtriouſly are theſe diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd, that not their deareſt friends, but their vileſt ſelves too fall by their own Cheats and Diſſimulation. And would the Impoſture rot with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But to ſee theſe <hi>Hyenae</hi> enſnare truly generous Souls, that are guilty of betraying nothing but themſelves, raiſeth ſo high an Indignation in me, that methinks every point I direct my pen to ſhould be the ſharp Execution of a ſtile at their hearts; for, if they have any, they have more than the <pb n="68" facs="tcp:104697:43"/>Creation form'd in them.</p>
               <p>But they have not yet their deaths wound, who outlive and outvie the transmutation of Cats themſelves: Suppoſe you ſaw ſuch a beautiful countenance at parting, orecaſt with an heavy cloud of ſeeming Sorrow, becauſe it leaves you perplexedly grieved: When inſtantly upon your vaniſhing it clears up all its beams and diſplays, to melt the next face and heart into a warm thaw, and court him as the Travailer out of his Cloak and modeſty, into the barefac'd nudities of luſt. Would you not wiſh with me ſuch a common red Lattice were alway as pervious to the eye, as ſignal in the paint; to abhorre at once the Goatiſh ſtench, loathſome impurities, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous embraces of a Brothel Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection?</p>
               <p>In the mean while how intire and meritorious ſoever your love be, it can have no fairer reception in her breaſt, than that Room which is the thorough-fare of a common Hoſtelry: <pb n="69" facs="tcp:104697:43"/>and here your Heart will be lodged; not under ſo conſecrate cuſtody and regard, as thoſe donaries and votive Tables, which ſome Sts. Chappels with oſtentation reckon up: But rather ſtrung up, as a long file of faln teeth, by which ſome vagrant Operator girds his Art about him; where if there be any of the Catalogue of greater eſteem than other, 'tis not for any kindneſs he ows it, or any its native excellecy, but from ſome extraordinary monſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity in it. I could hazard ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy with ſuch a Publican Soul, as might procure me but an inlet upon her thought, when ſhe is caſging, up the roll of her Copy-holders, and the duties they pay her: For I gueſs I ſhould find her careſſing her ſelf with greater delight, to have made ſo many Proſelytes, than pleaſure of fully gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying her enflamed Luſt, She may well admire that verſatile ſagacity of her skill, that has deluded and exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riated ſo many Booties, over whoſe innocent credulity, ſhe ſolennizeth and <pb n="70" facs="tcp:104697:44"/>inſulteth with the Soveraignty and Triumph of the haughty Scythian up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Caged Bajazet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can a man be willing to ſerve on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to fill up her Muſter, to increaſe the names muſt approve and licence her skill; that ſhe is one perfect in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of her Faculty; and of as refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diſſimulation as the Trade can bear? O Heavens! O tame Figures of Men! rather than want choler and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at this indignity, may you be all over icteritious. Could I wiſh worſe than theſe Miſcreants are forging upon themſelves, it ſhould be <hi>Caſſandra's</hi> deſtiny, to find none perſwaded by them: So far I pity, ſo much juſt wrath have I againſt theſe
<hi>Megaera</hi>'s, whoſe Hypocriſie may Entitle it ſelf another Fury of Hell (their bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Patrimony) and have Primacy of the other there. The very Beaſts can ſhew us out of their brutal appetite and converſe, nothing to be an Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphick of this Synopſis of Vice: The boſoms of theſe Wretches only, <pb n="71" facs="tcp:104697:44"/>encloſe this monſtrous propagation of promiſcuous evils, not to be conceiv'd in all <hi>Africa.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Ignes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuae,</hi> and Precipices too, of benighted and wandring Affections; the wanton touches upon pruriginous ſpirits, which inſtantly gripe with the ſtings and pangs of a Scorpion; the Velitation of a mad Sardian laughter, which termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates in mortal convulſions. Thoſe haggiſh <hi>Succubae,</hi> which not only drein the bloud of its pureſt vitals, but by Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite to the parched heart.</p>
               <p>Can I ſay more to awaken an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted ſoul, than that it is upon the margin of all horror? Open but your ſight to one beam of ſober and clear Reaſon, and you will be amaz'd to ſee how inſenſibly you have been hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and tranſported by theſe infernal Emiſſaries, to ſuch a diſtance from your own home and knowledge, and that in ſo ſhort a time: And if any good word may be now of force to diſſolve the charm you are under, <pb n="72" facs="tcp:104697:45"/>what ever this folly has coſt you; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me you cannot pay too dear for a Repentance that will ſnatch you out of their Gremial graves.</p>
               <p>In a word, theſe miſtreſſes of the Magiſtery of diſſimulation, are the greateſt Enemies to the convers of the World. For whereas nature im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed one royal and plain ſtamp on the noble mine of our Affections, Theſe firſt debaſe them with their droſs then form what impreſs ſoever they liſt to transfer upon them: So while we pay them with currant and ſolid maſs of unalloyed Love, they cheat and beggar us with exchange of their baſe obtruded Gounterfeits. And this is a myſtery they anvile without any noiſe, it needs no load nor tryal of Artizans tools: Their Hearts are the mineral, their Breaſts the hot forges, their Brain Hammer and Vice, their impudent looks, laſcivious words and wanton geſtures the expoſing ſtalls to their cozenage: their ware and ſhop how cheap and open ſoever, is yet <pb n="73" facs="tcp:104697:45"/>too dark and dangerous to advance one ſtep nearer perdition. Thus like dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Maſters they are born with the Engines of their Trade, and can ſet it up as eaſily as Tumblers vault; and without hardſhip of an Apprentiſhip become free of any Corporation. This is enough to decypher them to your knowledge without the infallibility of the Porphyry Chair. Avoyd them therefore as the moſt dreadful under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners of your liberty and happineſs; ſomewhat ſtoln upon the quiet of man again to caſt him out and bar Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe againſt us: which ſhall be charge enough to impeach thoſe ſeducing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and confirm you in your bleſſed Innocence.</p>
               <p>But I cannot have ſo great deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this herd of Satyrs, as venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that Love which is pure, and refulgent in the Conjugal or Amical Love-knot. I even adore that Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſpringing from a ſacred root ſprouts forth its ſtill flouriſhing bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms to enammel the fair plantations of <pb n="74" facs="tcp:104697:46"/>Nature with a perpetual Spring: The preſent, the after ages while time and mankind cohabite ſhall riſe up to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you with their due benedictions, and with the whole bank of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſhall acknowledge it ows its Stock to your liberal improvements. Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip I no leſs admire as one of the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granteſt flowers in the garden of the Creation, that Odor which delights the Soul with the ſympathy born from the ſame ſpot of Earth into an uniting coalition of Affections: Which in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſexes may ſometime grow into elegancies not otherwiſe educible: and if the terrene nouriſhment thereof be not too rich and luxuriant, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placencies of nature will by their fair attractions, more powerfully and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagingly corroborate and ſweeten it. But a true principle of Amity in all perſons and Relations, will not ceaſe to ſublime it ſelf into an Angelical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and innocence of Love; both in wiſhing nothing ſo much as one anothers happineſs, and purſuing it
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:104697:46"/>by all the amicable obligations and aſſiſtances of Virtue, with a caeleſtial effloreſcence of Joy, to have together aſcended above the dull and tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cares and hurries of unreaſonable paſſions; and be ſo farre emergent from ſenſe, as to diſtinguiſh and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat a condition that is ſerene, conge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, the Banquet of the moſt intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and amiable Spirits, and a prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libation of what the happy Glorious above enjoy and feaſt upon.</p>
               <p>But loe, we are brought down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to this groſs Orb of Grief and loſs, our Gallants Tragedy of</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>GAMING</head>
               <p>Where we find his Royalties and Mannors parceld and rent into a ſmall pack of Cards, his money ebbing and flowing with the pace it keeps to the rifing and falling Dice: all his hopes caſt into a narrow box; his deeds and conveyances in as little paper, as the Conqueror paſſ'd whole Countries o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <pb n="76" facs="tcp:104697:47"/>by. Not that our Gallants love Abridgments of our voluminous laws, much leſs a ſure and ſpeedy way to be rich: Nor do they curſe the tedious formalities of Tribunals. Only they admit of a diſtinct Court from <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall,</hi> from which no appeal is allowed: Every Ordinary has its So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon and Lycurgus; and as a particular Chancery expedites all the rules of its try'd and well conſulted Equity: and from theſe you ſhall ſometime meet our Gameſters return, with the countenances of thoſe that had juſt paſſ'd a Tryal at Bar. The famous Painter <hi>Angelo</hi> might from their looks have finiſht his laſt Judgment: The looſers bearing the gulfs of deſpair in their very faces, being undone and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected out of all their fair affluences, and ſo much as the hopes and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of having one caſt more for a Fortune: not one minute more of the whole ſtock of time to turn up a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable revolution; They themſelves Relations, dependents, expectancies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104697:47"/>and for ever debarr'd approach near to their abdicated proſperity. On the other ſide he might have the high ſpring-tides of exhilient Joy enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their channels, oreflowing all its banks to import an Ocean of new raiſ'd ſpirits, to welcome and take ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of the great ſucceſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the winner brings off: In whoſe look, not a Line Fear dares lay hold on, nor thorough this crowd of exultations can one ſad thought juſtle up to an Audience: And our Painter may fear to begin a Face ſo full of life, as all his skill and oyl, will be too little to tarifie and air, to brisk and rutilate.</p>
               <p>But thoſe in whom our Gaming can draw ſo pleaſant a Proſpect are indeed herein more like the bleſſed Heirs of Heaven; in that they are the rarer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Beatitude, ſome few ſelect reſerves of the collection of mankind, like the crowned Victors of the many that contended for the Prize, and loſt it. Only here our Gallants raſhly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the whole courſe to Fortune and <pb n="78" facs="tcp:104697:48"/>chance. Thoſe who exterminate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence may here behold, what fair proviſion they aſſign to the prudence and induſtry of the World, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it the unluckieſt advantage man could ſtumble on, to be born with eyes, endowed with underſtanding to diſcern happineſs, and a ſoul ſpirited to its enjoyment; but have no way diſtinguiſhable to ſeek after and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it, nor any means to retain it longer than the mutable contingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Affairs ſettle in one Poſture: For when the four ſtirring Elements, like the ſuits at Cards, are ſhuffled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another hand, or ſuch numbers fall into a benigne or croſs chance; there will be no bearing up againſt theſe blind events, and the Age muſt be left to play its own Game, and us; without any mediate diſpoſures or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our own.</p>
               <p>This would be to infatuate all the deſigns of reaſon and diligence. For though we know we muſt hazard ſtorms, unſeen rocks and ſhelves of <pb n="79" facs="tcp:104697:48"/>dangerous Seas; Yet who puts out, without his skilfull Pilot and Compaſs? Nay who puts himſelf upon the perils of waves, but on the faireſt expectancy of profitable returns? Only our home Adventurers here, that contract their whole ſubſtance into ſo little bulk, that they may eaſily heave all over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board at one lift, and caſt all away in one ſuddain wreck. Nor will they be adviz'd to beware of thoſe armed Land-Pirates, that lay ready to prey upon every ventur'd Eſtate, the arts they have to make out a Prize, their ſtratagems to hunt it, their violence and treachery invading it, and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs to divide the ſpoil in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſight of the naked Gull. So do we often ſee an old ſtout Carrack, that has made many a ſucceſsful honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and rich voyage; that has long carried all the fortune, name, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a brave Family embarkt in it: neither ſplit on the fatall hardneſs of the times, nor broken by fury of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Tempeſts, or loſt by its old in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcoverably <pb n="80" facs="tcp:104697:49"/>growing leakages; no, nor yet nobly ſunk after manly reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance by the prevailing enemy of its nation: But baſely aſſail'd by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſpected crew of Villains in the very harbor; unladen, pillaged, and cleft into ſo ſmall planks, that you find not ſo much of it remain, as of our great Drakes veſſel to be but a narrow Seat of that once famous name.</p>
               <p>What the admirable wiſdome and conduct of your Anceſtors gathered into one ſafe Hive, to be the ſtock and ſhelter of the whole Tribe; to Head &amp; Countenance; to all the Line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; One night ſurprizeth, deſtroys, the Oeconomy of the Family, extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes the fair Colonies it might have peopled the world with; and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains nothing of it but the ſhade of a great Name; the empty curtail of its faint Eccho. I know no law can be form'd to prevent theſe frequent miſcarriages, wherein Poſterity ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers abortion, and many a pregnant Spirit is ſuffocated, in the ſtreight en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſures <pb n="81" facs="tcp:104697:49"/>of a confining vellicating For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: who had they opportunity of fairly lanching forth, their ſails had been fill'd with the ſame breath of their Ages Honour, and Applauſe, which was a propitious gale to their Grand-fathers: whereas now your own fartheſt extended Line ſhall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your name, but to laſh it with their heavieſt execrations. For the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of the whole by your exportation and alienation of what was theirs more than yours, has alſo like the
<hi>Peter</hi>-pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhip ſtranded in <hi>Sandwich,</hi> together with it ſank the Harbor; and made its convenient ſituation more regretfully deplorable in the ſad diſaſter. For it is a miſery to be born to the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thoſe honors, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and ſenſe of our preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digencies ſuffer us only to grieve o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſink in that alſo below the calamity and loſs it ſelf.</p>
               <p>I could wiſh there were kept a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter in each ſhire of all, who, by this or any other profuſion, end as the <pb n="82" facs="tcp:104697:50"/>Snuffs of noble and wealthy deſcents, that their Country may exclaim at and abominate the ſtench; And that ſome proportion of every fair Revenue might by no Law niceties be alienable; but, upon ſuch a declination of the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, immediately paſs into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties poſſeſſion: not to erect Hoſpitals for the <hi>devaſtator,</hi> but be wholly converted to the education of the moſt hopeful Youth can be recommended (thoſe of that Name primarily reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) for the making up the breach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and raiſing up as flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing a name again to the Nation. Nor can your ſeverity be too rigid upon the ſpend-thrift, who has ſubmitted himſelf and Fortune (as the Military diſcipline ſometime does its offenders lives) to the lot upon the Drum-head, and his poſterity under the Spear to infamous ſlavery and ſufferings: Spirits ſo ignobly baſe, that, were their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers duſt intruſted on their inheritance, would even pawn their quiet aſhes and old monuments, to build one poor bank at play.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:104697:50"/>
               <p>Theſe are leſs worthy our commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration, than the many Malefactors we with dry eies follow to Execution. He that ſalcheth or robbs on the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way is not in hope of ſuch booties, nor capacity to deſtroy more than ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle lives: Here we ſee play'd away the lives and beings of thoſe, they have no more juſt power to diſpoſe of, than the Church has, to alienate its conſecrate rights to profane abuſes; or than we can force of ſatisfaction, for the cruelty, and rapines of <hi>Romans</hi> and
<hi>Danes</hi> upon our Fore-fathers. I might add to the ſhame of our Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants madneſs, what their hopes of gain can be upon their greateſt ſucceſs. Did you ever ſee any great Family made greater by acceſſions at Play? Certainly Induſtry and honeſt Labor raiſ'd all that we now ſee, bearing up above the malice and fate of old Time: An Eſtate thus built has no one rafter but is ſeaſoned, every ſtone has the ſtability of a Quarry; 'tis ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with long wrought ſweat, and <pb n="84" facs="tcp:104697:51"/>is a morſel on which <hi>Saturn</hi> himſelf will break his fangs: What we gain by fair diligence has a ſweetneſs, which ſtollen waters ſhall ſooner become wine than emulate, a ſweetneſs which from the ſoundneſs of its conſtitution forbids corruption; and muſt needs conſerve every particular, as being the condiment of Time it ſelf: which would be ſo burthenſome to us, that were there no induſtry neceſſary, to till, ſow, and reap our fields, our bread and life would be alike embittered to us. All your gains at play can never be adopted to ſerious and noble uſes, like the I holoze Gold, and all Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious ſpoils, they rather bring a Coal to conſume your own high-raiſ'd hopes and Fortunes: Thoſe that rob you, are anon under the pilferings of their own vicious Luſts; and the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels that depend on Events of as great ſucces evey day will find their own Family unprovided for.</p>
               <p>I will joyn to this Quixotry its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable Sancho through all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures <pb n="85" facs="tcp:104697:51"/>of Gaming; that bears the weapons; and Portmantua full of Lightning and Thunder: I mean the</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SWEARING</head>
               <p>That attends Gameſters; which is ſo much the more inexcuſable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all this while our Gallants muſt play with as little concern and regret as the <hi>Don</hi> had, whether he did beat or was beaten; the generoſity of his ſpirit and glory of the Adventurers would not bear a ſecond beating by his own paſſions. But certainly that great
<hi>Iſabella,</hi> who in her extremities of Childbirth cover'd her face, and not ſo much as by her looks would derogate from Majeſty; could not ſo quietly look on the intrenchments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her ſtate and Soveraignty, but would paſſionately aſſert it, againſt her own <hi>Ferdinand.</hi> And I will not believe Oaths and Curſes, becauſe they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent our ordinary Language, and are uſed to veil many natural defects, <pb n="86" facs="tcp:104697:52"/>ſound no more when we part with an arm or limb of an Eſtate. If they are not all this while in paſſion, theſe might have been well ſpared; if they be, theſe like bellows blow it into grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heat and fury: and this can be but the very blowing away an overture to an excuſe.</p>
               <p>However theſe are the Gameſters, Artillery, and Trumpets too: if they come off with a fair Atchievment, theſe proclaim the Prize; if worſted, they ſound the foile too. They have not Oaths enough to magnifie and invoke Fortune in her favourable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: Nor ever hope to be reveng'd of her frowns, by belching up their haſty and fowl execrations on the Mig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. As temerariouſly and blindly they caſt round about them theſe fire-brands and fatal ponyards, as ſhe ſeems to them wantonly to diſpenſe her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinies. But where the Fire catches, and the Wounds fall, the Nature of this fulminant Gold will lowdly direct you: You think to blow and ſhoot
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:104697:52"/>it up againſt Heaven; but it kindles below, and breaks downward, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyling fearfully, with the noiſe and burning of a Cannon upon your own boſom.</p>
               <p>Might I enquire what theſe bold Gigantic Combatants think of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, or a ſurer hand guiding their Game: If there be none, why do the Brutes ſo rave, at what do they diſcharge their continual brayings, why ſo tormentouſly rend their weary throats? If there be a Fortune, She is blind and unconcern'd. Why ſhould they commit their hopes and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the Winds? But if indeed you ſtrive with Heaven; 'tis becauſe you can ſubject its decrees to yours, or fear them not: If the firſt, you only are in fault if you be not as happy as you would be: Conquered, frighted Heaven muſt have ſtoop'd to your commands. Why complain you far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of it? If the latter ſteel your au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciouſneſs, They are very impotent and deſpicable cannot reach, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <pb n="88" facs="tcp:104697:53"/>your daring impieties. Be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident however, this is not the way to call down caeleſtial auxiliaries (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Spirits are willing to anſwer hard and terrible words) your defian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces arm them againſt you, to powr down greater fury, to compleat and triumph in your extremeſt miſery.</p>
               <p>But our Gallants plead not ſo much the ventilation of Paſſion, the explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion only of ſome fired diſcontented Spirits by their curſed Oaths (where. I cannot conceive the Devil for their Example) They uſe them as the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies and figures of ſpeech, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as the Ornaments of their dreſs. They are their ſupplements unto all parts of diſcourſe and Rhetoric: Oaths and imprecations file off all rudeneſs and barbariſms, act the full force of perſwaſion, and the very acuteneſs of a declamation and Satyr. They can be as ill layd down by our Nobleſs as their Muffs in winter, ſo frigid and ſhrivel'd would their converſe be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. They have a way to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize <pb n="89" facs="tcp:104697:53"/>much of their great minds in this kind of Laconic brevity. Their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Coachmen, and Watermen with but one round mouth'd Ejaculation, and a hand toward their ſword, ſtraight know what they mean, and, as Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els are taught, readily execute their pleaſure. The ſame again breath'd with a melting accent, ſmooth face, and bending body, ſerves in the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſences of complements, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts of moſt oblieging friendſhip and ſervice.</p>
               <p>O depraved times, and more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Humanity! Is there no way left us to be ingenious, and facetious, but by obſcenities or monſtrous abuſe of all that is ſacred? Does Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and contempt of Divinity encir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle our Wits with that Laurel, which will both dare the Thunderer, and evade the blow! Then let us yield them immortality, and dread the ſtroaks of their incenſed Wit, as the vulgar doe the tails of Comets, and the multiplication of Suns. But if we <pb n="90" facs="tcp:104697:54"/>reflect on the genuine evaporations of theſe Ingenioſo's, how like are they to Meteors, and Hurricanes of wit, rather than fixed ſtars, or the Heaven born placid and fructifying Dew: ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lowd foaming forced and angry Torrents; than the ſmooth and Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalline ſtream flowing eaſily from a pure Fountain of happy invention? That which can run with an even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted vein of fertile ingeny and knowledge, thorough all the wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Art and Nature; Sometime emptying it ſelf in the profound ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of abſtruſe Philoſophy, to try the moſt reaching fathom; Anon, playing with and turning up the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſands, reſting on the ſides of the courted ſhoars, crisping its light divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding waves into limpid curls, with whispred purling murmurs; as if wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving into bracelets, and with its ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died muſick obliging its Muſes ſtay and delight. 'Tis the facility and ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Wit alone can impregnate the moſt barren Subject, make a Garden
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:104697:54"/>of a Common, contrive an oregrown Forreſt into a Grove, or innocent La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth; cut a rocky Precipice into a delightful Grott, and Waterworks; and is at no knotty emergency ſo ſtopt and plung'd, that it needs to call a Deity down upon the ſtage, to make its way open and diſembogued.</p>
               <p>Since then the eſſentials of true wit are of a different Origination and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, from the Spurious attempts of thoſe who laying their titles ſo bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from Heaven, are but the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous race of Centaurs, and far from Demi-Gods; Let the Nobles confeſs their miſtake, when they find this cloud break in noiſe and ſmoak, and include no other
<hi>Juno:</hi> And may they the more eaſily quit this ſuperfluity of Vice, as what ſounds with no other effect than the vanity of Childrens Potguns and Crackers. 'Tis a wickedneſs yields ſo little preſent ſatisfaction, and may ſo eaſily be ſhut out of all diſcourſe; that it is the huge amazement of ſober men, that any will venture paying <pb n="92" facs="tcp:104697:55"/>dear for ſo fond a Lubency. That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, which would be not only inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent but delightful, is often thus ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiced, and made too poynant with ſprinkling thoſe hot and high Oaths and Curſes: that our ſpirits are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the air they breath, like nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles and launcets piercing a tender and ſedate Soul; at the ſame time ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the wounds deeper with regrett, to be ſo unhappily bound and ſow'd up in a bag, with nettles and Waſps.</p>
               <p>This Vice may more decently now alſo be relinquiſhed as being the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar of their very Lacquays, the Blazonry of the dregs of the Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. In births, cloaths, diet, diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the heightning your pleaſures; in the melioration of your minds by education and converſe, in your hopes, deſigns, and noble employments you far outſtrip all their enjoyments, and attempts: But here they can Rival (I doe not ſay) outvie you, in number, volubility, and as lowd volleys of Oaths and execrations. Now it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns <pb n="93" facs="tcp:104697:55"/>your Honour to retire, leave them the ſport and quarry, which is not worth your Time, and does but diſhoneſt your truly noble Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>You may here make a moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble experiment upon the world (moſt docible by Examples that deſcend) You have convey'd this curſed ſound through the whole Iland in an inſtant; as in the whiſpring pipes, the Roman wall is ſaid to have carry'd in ſo long a Traverſe. Would you might be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to change theſe harſh and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſounds into ſoft and peaceable, that the affrighments and Furies, thoſe have alarm'd, may be appeas'd; and we may appear to be ſeriouſly buſie; not tumultuouſly ſtartled and hurryed together as to an uproar and Riot: You may hence inform us, whether ſignal Virtue can be as exemplary as Vice has been by imitation deſtructive. So may you recover the reputation your births have given you above the commonalty, and your Faith remain <pb n="94" facs="tcp:104697:56"/>inviolable: That your but neceſſary aſſeverations upon your Generoſity and Honour, may be reverenced in your ſelves, and ſacred in the eſteem of your Inferiours.</p>
               <p>We ſhould now at laſt be groſly deluded, if we expect to find Religion in thoſe Perſons we ſtruck at in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our diſcourſe: For none of thoſe Vices can be the Rule of that Profeſſion we have eſpouſed: No ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er a word and power than</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ATHEISM</head>
               <p>Regulates theſe mens lives, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldens their impieties. With this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraliſſimo of the Powers of darkneſs, this skirmiſh ſhall be concluded, as that (which ſome gloſſe) the race of man ſhall at laſt ſet and conclude in. And now indeed, when we ſee the notion of a Deity uſurp'd, but as the occult qualities to be derided only and exploded: We cannot but find the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows growing and ſtealing apace up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:104697:56"/>us. But certainly 'tis an affectation of obſcurity envelopes us in night, and ſhuts out thoſe raies, which cannot but in every point clear up to us the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Creator. 'Tis groſſe Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Inconſideration, malitious wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the world, that dares not, will not admit a God into their thoughts, to become the Supreme Arbiter of their hearts and lives. Therefore they perplex their brains to diſpute it off the ſtage. and with far greater anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties labor to entangle the conception of a Deity, than they can ſo much as ſuppoſe in acknowledging their makers infinite perfections.</p>
               <p>For ſhall fond man, whom we eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day ſee crumbling into Earth, that knows not his own beginning nor ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, his compoſition nor capacity, judge of thoſe things which as infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſcend our comprehenſion, as Nature; and could be no longer ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable if not perfectly myſterious? ſhall ſhallow we, loſt in diving but to the bottom of every ſenſible, hope to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom <pb n="96" facs="tcp:104697:57"/>the immenſe Abyſs of all power, knowledge, goodneſs? Would you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer worſhip, love, or fear God, if you had an apprehenſion of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which you could any where ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in finite limits? This would be to heathenize the Earth again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch a ſlight and formal venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as heretofore was beſtowed on their race of Gods, that once grew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves; and on the Idols they ſhaped according to their own phanſied Images. I need not ſay it is neceſſary, for it is impoſſible, we ſhould here have any more plain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Maker, than thoſe in which He is pleaſed to reveal himſelf to us. All of the knowledge of himſelf is my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious, adorable, admirable, but moſt conſummate: All of our Duty plain, eaſie, and moſt neceſſary. I ſay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the reaſonableneſs thereof, that if it had been no Tryal of the will and affections to renounce the world and our ſelves, God would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have propounded it in the middle <pb n="97" facs="tcp:104697:57"/>between an Eternal Glory and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
               <p>But it is a vain Curioſity (which firſt made the breach upon Man in the maſs) which will not be confin'd to its duty, under our preſent poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and hopes, greater than man can raiſe his vaſt ſoul to contrive. The ſtate of which happineſs, becauſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring upon no avenue of our ſenſes; nay above all the reaches of our what not amplifying Heart, and almoſt powerfully creating Imagination; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds our conceptions and belief of it. But doe I believe God the maker of this fair fabric of this viſible Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; wherein every one phanſies he could carve out portion large enough for his moſt importunate deſires: and in the poor pittances, fragments and Atoms whereof we every day ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny repoſing their utmoſt felicity, and could be content to ſing eternal Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems to their Souls over them? Do I not herein alſo admire the wonderful delight, beauty, uſe, and harmony re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting <pb n="98" facs="tcp:104697:58"/>from every part of it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centring within my ſelf in fulleſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and content, from my contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and fruitions thereof? And ſhall I not now be confident, that the moſt wiſe Creator, that raiſed this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous frame but as a Pavilion to be ſpread over Pilgrims, or a ſtately Theatre for ſome few daies exhibiting the various Scenes and Actors upon the world, and then be taken down, has a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of infinitely more excelling work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip and entertainment; that the happineſs reſerv'd muſt tranſcend what ſoever I can ſee lovely and deſirable here in my paſſage, and therefore muſt be <hi>Heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where the yellow clay, glaſſe beads and pebbles we reckon our ſelves and riches by (in our Sanguine dreams here) which we fear under our kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and bitterly bewail being loſt; All theſe will be contemptible to the diaphanous yet ſolid Sun of the metals, pearls, and truly precious ſtarry Gems; which are not to be the treaſures but
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:104697:58"/>materials of the Caeleſtial manſions. The ſatisfaction I now take in one good word or work virtuouſly accompliſht, will then paſs into a feſtival of Joy, by being aſſerted into a bliſsful activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all goodneſs, to the utmoſt of my enlarged powers. The refined pleaſure my Soul now takes in, with every freſh gleam, and diſcovery of New found knowledge, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a truth conſentaneous to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of my own reaſon; ſhall then be the quickning it ſtill to move on the inexhauſtible deeps of Science and wiſdome, with free expanſions, and heliotrope converſions to that eternal light; that will irradiate and inform the intellectuals with the Spirit of all underſtanding. The affection of love, which here at ſome time carrys me out, to a delight and union with any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive amiableneſs, and my raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the harmonious repercuſſions of a Beloved, ſhall there tranſport me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o one endleſs Extaſie of Love; where I ſhall enjoy what can alone (without
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:104697:59"/>grating on any one affection) perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually invite out and meet the Soul in its pureſt ardencies and zeal, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extinguiſhable freeneſs, and fulneſs of divine goodneſs and bounty: ſo that this inconceivable energy the ſoul ſhall feel, will carry it wholly forth to the Viſion of Beatitude, and paſs it into the Glory it ſees, adores, and loves with endleſs Delectation. Now then if I may have leave to call the will of the Bleſſed Souls, purity; their underſtanding, all eie; all their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Love: You will think the world you now live in a ſink of Vice; a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern of dark ignorance; and a den of monſtrous and ſalvage malice and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty.</p>
               <p>Could I here alſo pourtray the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors a dejected, guilty, aſtoniſhed, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, deſpairing, and ſelf-torturing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which way ſoever it turns, feels, and fears; I ſhould from our own ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which are often ſabled with me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, from the ravings of a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the pangs and groans of acute <pb n="101" facs="tcp:104697:59"/>pains, and deathbed agonies and ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, ſay enough to confeſs, though not conſtitute the miſery of an Hell. Both theſe ſtates with all the notions our narrow conceptions form of them, having all the demonſtrations our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and the nature of the thing can admit, nothing being wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to convince and ſupport the moſt penetrating and cautelous Reaſon; let us no longer deny their being and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, becauſe ſo incomprehenſibly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove us, and ours. For I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as to a diſtinct and clear appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of them, we are as incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, as the Embryo is in the cloſe and dark womb to conceive of the vaſtneſs, order, and beauty of this lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger neſt of Nature; wherein the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon you will alſo find to be more ſtreightned. From your enjoyments here only conſider whether you think the Author of them could not have heightned and perpetuated them, had it ſeemd good to infinite wiſedom.</p>
               <p>We in all theſe behold a continual <pb n="102" facs="tcp:104697:60"/>viciſſitude various interchanges and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of all things ſublunary. And it may not be amiſs to grant ſuch a rotation of States and families; as may ſuppoſe that they have all had their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual portion of proſperity and adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo alſo that the very higheſt and loweſt pitch and fall of either have, in ſome age or other, made ſome of the ſame ſtock moſt eminent in both conditions: that in every line ſome may be accountable for the truſt of Princely power, and tryal of meaneſt debaſement. However in all the varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our affairs here below, we may eaſily ſee and admire a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence diſpoſing them, and bearing up a moſt conſtant tenour of unerring re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity: That days and ſeaſons have their unalterable returns, the minds and ſhapes of each man their proper ſentiments and impreſſes, every nation its particular diſtinct genius, the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and excellency of each ſo counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiz'd (even to the turning with the two hundredth part of a grain) by <pb n="103" facs="tcp:104697:60"/>ſome other defects and virtues of a neighbour Countrey, to the ſetting of due bounds to all: For the wilyneſs of that ballanceth the ſtrength of this; the heat and agility of another is temper'd by the Phlegm and induſtry of their Enemy: to their innate ambition, is oppos'd the inexpungnable zeal others have to their native ſoil. Thus we ſee the Empires of the world have their periods, declination and expiration; as well as a Riſe, augmentation, and flouriſhing.</p>
               <p>That the conceptions and deſigns of every individual admit ſo many tranſmutations with their years; and that all of them ſooner or later retire, and clear the ſtage to another Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to which muſt be committed the whole concerns of Mankind; and yet all this while among ſo different traverſes, the world has faln into no decay; no Encroachments have been made on Nature; nor ſuch inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on its Inhabitants as to drown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their ſpecific temperaments, or <pb n="104" facs="tcp:104697:61"/>ſo oreflow any one part of them, as not to be recovered in ſome revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; does lowdly proclaim and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the moſt wiſe decretals ef Heaven, managing ſo many diſſenting heads, and new hands to the carrying on the wonderful buſineſs of Providence. There is no novelty under the Sun, all will ſtill proceed with the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of a man, if we do not put off our own natures and principles. For 'tis Atheiſm alone can unhinge all, and invert the whole order of things; by deſtroying all opinion of the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and integrity of former ages, the happy ſecurity of the preſent, and all concerns and hopes for the future.</p>
               <p>But had we a conſiderative view into the cauſes, actings, and termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thoſe grand occurrences, which firſt ſtartle, then leave us as much careleſs as unſatisfied; we ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the deep agencies of Providence. Did every one but ſeriouſly regard the wonders that have ſignaliz'd a great part of his own private concerns <pb n="105" facs="tcp:104697:61"/>and contingencies; the notices ariſing thence would ſhew how he had been acted and guided by another hand and intention, beſide and beyond his own. Round about how many notable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances daily break forth to inſtruct us, that Blind Nature alone could not ſo happily Time and finiſh her wiſe miſtakes? As Embryos we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive much of the Order and Power of the Intellectual World. But I am perſwaded much more is done among us by the concurrence of good and Evil Spirits, in common converſe and Accidents, than we imagine or obſerve. Had we an hiſtory of thoſe unaccountable remedies (which are no ſmall nor unwarranted part of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine) ſome from animals, other from Vegetables, taken inwardly, or uſed as Amulets; we ſhould acknowledge a great deal to their benignity, or ſome permitted deluſions in their diſcoveries. The Temple of
<hi>Aeſculapius</hi> famous for its cures preſcribed in dreams, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred into a Diſpenſatory on the <pb n="106" facs="tcp:104697:62"/>walls therof; beſide many later re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markables of this nature, juſtifies this my conceit.</p>
               <p>Withal I ſuppoſe them very prone, if not by rule diſpoſed, to concern themſelves in all ſorts of Offices, wherein they may employ their powerful activities; and have the pleaſure unſeen, to guide, aſſiſt, and patronize many of our undertakings. Many ſudden and uncouth friendſhips, antipathies, ſtrange deliverances, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices in extraordinary diſtances, ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of intricacies, preſages, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful influences upon other Creatures I may favourably refer to their preſence and miniſtery; not denying but there are ſome perſons by nature and temper (without recourſe to an Aſteriſm) fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to wonderful intimations, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances beyond the Vulgar. Yet I cannot but admire to ſee ſome ſuddenly grown up into an opinion and repute with the World; wonderfully made the darlings of Fortune, from one lucky article of an occaſion inſtantly <pb n="107" facs="tcp:104697:62"/>outſtripping all others, and their own thoughts; thrive and proſper to the amazement of all, where every one before was defeated and waſted; in every enterprize and but petty hazard ſucceſsful and victorious: and all this without anxious ſolicitudes, laborious inſudations, or more than Common ſtock of comprehenſion or contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance. At the ſame time, a perſon wherein nothing is wanting to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, as well as ſtrength and vigor of Reaſon and Prudence, no defect in induſtry and Art; ſinking, unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, every way oppreſſed, and quite broken in all his deſignments: When I preſently reflect on the admonition gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Mark Antonie,</hi> in his competitions with
<hi>Auguſtus;</hi> and that there is more truth and myſtery in it, than we are aware of, and advized by. On a due collection, you will conclude, even where all ſeems to lay open to the ſports and frolikes of Time and Chance, a moſt ſure Hand from above, beyond our determinations and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:104697:63"/>reaches, diſpoſes all events how ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual ſoever in appearance and (by many Inſtruments [perhap] of ſome nearer degree of Intellectual Agents.)</p>
               <p>From the promiſcuous ſucceſſes and conditions, Virtue and Vice are here equally involved in with induſtry and Imprudence, you may as neceſſarily infer the conſequence of a ſtate of life after this; where one ſhall account for the impious abuſes of long provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and moſt attractive goodneſs; the other meet a remuneration, ſuitable to the exerciſe of a ſuffering, throughly tryed, and perfected integrity. To which I may joyn the inſatiable thirſt, the ſoul of man pants under, toward a ſtate of immortality: It beholds it ſelf made to diſtinguiſh, and comprehend, the truth and worth of all about it (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the power it ſees any other Creature born unto) But there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great a part of it undiſcovered upon the Continent, as well as wide Ocean of knowledge; All the principles hereof alſo being but precariouſly and <pb n="109" facs="tcp:104697:63"/>dubiouſly admitted; How does the Soul lay down and bewail it's ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, finding it's cleareſt reſolves and concluſions, ſubject to cavillation and torture, when raiſing up an appetite large enough to take in the coveted delicacies, appearing only as if but to tantalize it? But now that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which meets us heated, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, dejected in deſpair of ever reaching, what our greedineſs has tranſported us out after; how well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, pleaſant, ſatisfactory will it be to us; reviving and raiſing us up again on our feet, ſo as to forget all our paſt toil and wearineſs; Eſpecially when to the poſſeſſion of this Terreſtrial knowledge, It bids us look up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above, and reckon upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Lights and worlds of wiſdom and underſtanding there, which we are created capable to look and paſs into, and ſhall eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally reſide under their illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</p>
               <p>We ſhall ſuddenly then make up <pb n="110" facs="tcp:104697:64"/>the arrears of the longeſt lives (and an hundred years are brought into as ſmall a point as twenty, to the review of a dying perſon.) The Philoſophy, we grope after all the ſhort night of our duration here, will (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) by the firſt approaches of the light of our never ſetting day, be plain and illuſtrate to us: The Firſt and Wiſeſt of Men had not larger notices of the Creation, than the uncaptiv'd Spirit inſtantly enters upon; for that (as <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt) is born and ſprings forth from it's clay, arrayed with the ſame connate beams of knowledge as of life. And the wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> was that Celeſtial <hi>Chariſma,</hi> which in it's very illapſes enlarged his Soul to it's reception. Thus ennobled, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit riſes to the dignity of an Empyreal Gueſt, preſently as it feels it ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacled from duſt, and above it's diſtreſſes and fears, finding eternal joys ſet wide open to him: Otherwiſe it would be a ſurprize of ſuch amazing happineſs, enough to make it fall into <pb n="111" facs="tcp:104697:64"/>ſuch a Syncope it left the body in, were it not inſtantly transform'd and adapted with generous inſtincts of it's Glorious inheritance. To demonſtrate the quick diſpatch of ſo great a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, it's means and methods, you ſhall reſpite me; Till you find any one determine the inſtant and manner of the Souls connexion to the body, and the affections it brought with it: Or let another tell me how long time he is learning to ſee, and by what degrees he apprehends the benefit and uſe of light: Or a Third when he firſt knew he had Reaſon, and what was to be done by it: Or another ſhew, how an Antipathy or Sympathy immediately break forth, and act all their violences, without calling the Soul down to Counſel.</p>
               <p>'Tis enough, that theſe, and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable Truths, are not only the ſubject of our rational examinations, but ſhall once be the convictions and experiences of our apprehenſions: which affords me a wide field of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <pb n="112" facs="tcp:104697:65"/>that the unhappy curioſity of our Nature; which has (I believe) drawn many to converſe with any order of Spirits; Either that they might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the being of ſuch Creatures, or from them gain ſome intelligence and notices above ordinary diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; do's not produce in us all an extraordinary ſatisfaction and delight, in the knowing that Truth which is our Light and Way to arrive at a bleſſed Communion, and Union with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Fountain of all Spiritual be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. I cannot, to the higheſt Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, urge a greater cogency of their duty to their Creator. The very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to the Father of our Spirits inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate no leſs than our return to, and quiet, in that boſome which delighted to give us a being: And to be brought to the knowledge and favor of the moſt pure Origine of all Spirits as ſtrongly imports our arrival, at that Center of Truth and happineſs, which is the Summe of All that created be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings can poſſibly know or enjoy. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:104697:65"/>will your capacities be contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but as infinite Perfection is the object of your Fruitions, ſo will your Souls (emptyed of the burthens, and coarctation of incumbring matter) be dilated and ſtretched out, into your proportionable entertainments of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowing Beatitude. And what more can any deſire than he can enjoy? The Soul it ſelf can go no farther; becauſe it cannot, need not to, deſire any thing more.</p>
               <p>And thoſe that are in ſuch eager queſt of the Cheifeſt Good and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent happineſs, will find the Soul poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of uninterrupted Joy, and Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; only as enjoying the favor of the Moderator of all things. The quiet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and fixation flowing from this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance no diſtractions, incertitudes or impediments abroad can intercept, or diminiſh: And hence you will have an Argument as full as it's brevity will bear, to invite your Soul to trample on all the droſs and defilements, which ſteal away your hearts, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct <pb n="114" facs="tcp:104697:66"/>your early engroſſing of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and aſcent to Heaven.</p>
               <p>As ignorance is the Parent of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, ſo is Atheiſm the unhappy birth of Inconſideration: That is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to reſt on any thing; this repudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, and careleſly rejects all: that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſobriety and attention; and this, becauſe the inconſiderate will not be at leiſure, thoroughly to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with any thing, much leſs themſelves. Would they be ſo kind to their own Souls to hear what they can ſay for their own Original, how they derive their Genealogy by Authentic Patents from Heaven above; they would not ſo eaſily relinquiſh their Title to it, &amp; paſs away their primoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture for every ready meſs of Vanity. Nor do they underſtand more of the reſt of the World, and regard all they know as little, as if wholly Ignorant of it. They live as on a wide open Ocean, where every wave and wind com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them from Anchor; whither they cannot, nor care to learn. How <pb n="115" facs="tcp:104697:66"/>'tis with them they cannot inform you, nor how they would have it, nor what they ſhall be next day, or year; much leſs, all their life time.</p>
               <p>While He that own's a Providence, and depends upon it, has one certain ſcope to which he directs all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and moderates all his hopes and fears, in a certain perſwaſion of the Divine Wiſdom Supremely diſpoſing him, and all Events for the beſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. So that, among the greateſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies and utmoſt beauty of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nothing is more fair and lovely, than the uniform obedience, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant acquieſcence of the Good Soul with his Makers Commands and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fure; to be without the rule and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port whereof, would be his very Hell, as tormenting as it would be deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to him: For 'tis that extirpates his doubts, and dark ratiocinations to a moſt ſatisfactory ſubmiſſion. Hence is he that Cube, which way ſoever turn'd, ſtill reſting on the ſame equal
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:104697:67"/>Square. So that he can be as infallible in the conjectures of himſelf, through the many hidden changes of Futurity, and whatſoever ſhall on any juncture occur; as he can ſafely and contentedly judge of his preſent ſtate of life and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment.</p>
               <p>The reſt of the world have their minds ſtill under ſuſpenſe, as ſo many Crows met and hovering over ſome Carrion; Or as a looſe flight of Atoms broken and wafting away from them, and they left an empty lodging for the next kind gale of a new life and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. For here they live without any determinate and proper deſignment of life to bind them together; they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver account with themſelves for what purpoſe they live, not what they aim at, or where they would reſt: but from this, haſt to another delight, and ſo to the next; Still upon the wing, and ſtill frighted, or tyred off, from their enjoyments. Thus they, like meer ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive beings, neither know, nor have any other buſineſs of life, but ſtill to live <pb n="117" facs="tcp:104697:67"/>on, as far as they can go, in the meer determinations of Matter and Motion: Like thoſe Creatures altogether, who are but the plainer and ruder pieces of Workmanſhip, to the nobler and moſt exquiſite frame of the body of man: they being as it were made but with one ſingle and eaſie motion, but we with the wonderful movements, of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner complications<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of wheels within one another: The obſervation of that Great Luminary of Philoſophy and Phyſic, from whoſe unwearied abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and penetrations Anatomical, I beg leave to borrow one of Singular conſideration, diſtinguiſhing the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginry which our Spirits employ, of more ſpecial and curious contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, than are to be found in other ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals.</p>
               <p>In his accurate diſcovery of the uſe of the Intercoſtal nerves, in the fair branches thereof Communicated to the Region of the Heart, He main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: that by theſe are kept up a continued commerce between the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:104697:68"/>Brain and Heart: ſo that hence are derived advices of each others affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and all the diverſity of their phancies and ſentiments. Divinity and Nature hitherto teaching us that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's reſidence is in the Heart: we here (ſays the ſame admirable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) learn it to be rather in its clear concluſions, from the conferences and conſtant intercourſes between the Heart and Brain, and that this reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal correſpondence maintains the heat and light of mutual intelligence; and, duly interchanged, perfects our moſt complete intendments of Virtue and Prudence. Diſſecting a Natural, this texture of Nerves was found very ſmall and of fewer ſtrings than that branch in man oridnarily grows up with. In the body of an Ape this ſhooting forth ſome few inſertions toward the heart twined its fibres with the Nerve of the Diaphragm. Hence he infers this Creature has its ingeny and docility, not only expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing us in our geſtures, but even to <pb n="119" facs="tcp:104697:68"/>ſome faint reſemblances of our very manners and affections.</p>
               <p>Thus far that Inimitable Profeſſor gives us light to our Brain and Heart to judge that they would be thought, in this ſtupendous Fabric, not the bare conflux only of looſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms; But that we have a body inſtructed to execute the orders of the Nobler Soul, and to act in joynt Commiſſion with it; in a faithful ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of thoſe diſtinct regular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, their moſt wiſe Creator de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd them unto: beyond the utmoſt abilities of the neareſt order, and moſt ſimilar of all inferior Creatures. So that for man to own no dependence on his Maker, not to raiſe his thoughts to the contemplation, and adoration of that hand, which ſtretch'd out the rule of his being and motions, and length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens out all his lines as ſeems good to It, is to renounce the Heart and Brain of a reaſonable being; And like the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Monarch while he views the ſtately and glorious built of his body, <pb n="120" facs="tcp:104697:69"/>Cry out in a Philoſophic Rapture; Is not this the wonderful Machine of Nature, which I with the ſtrength of my deep wiſdom have found to be rais'd upon my own Atoms, and can to my Honor ennoble theſe very particles with excellent Ornaments and Riches, out of the ſtore of my own admirable Underſtanding, which ſoars above the low and timorous flight of Vulgar knowledge, and ſcorns to own any Deity to Rival me in the boundleſs Empire of my ſelf-advancing Reaſon, Will, and Affections? Do we not, preſently upon theſe haughty Rodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montad's, ſee the juſt decree of the Great Watcher fulfilled upon the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantic Sophies? Who turning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Commons with the Beaſts, and refuſing to hold of the Sovereignty of Heaven, forfeit the ſhape &amp; heart of Man: nor ſill up the buſineſs of their life with the true deſigns of Prudence and Virtue; to the happineſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they were in their very make and motions born and inſtructed.</p>
               <p>But the Soul, whoſe foundations are <pb n="121" facs="tcp:104697:69"/>laid on unerring Providence, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions enlarg'd and raiſed to a perfect dependence and conformity with the mind of Heaven, can now truly ſay (what another Emperor as fondly vaunted, when his vaſt Palace was contrived) that now at length it has began to live like a man.</p>
               <p>The ſum of all is this, theſe Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates of the world of knowledge, loſe themſelves and the knowledge of their God, in the Miſt of their affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ignorance and inconſideration. They that think nothing impenetrable to their ſharp Judgment, and that their underſtandings are large enough to draw in the Ocean of all Science; a Fly ſtraying into their Eye, blunts and blinds the one; and a few Atoms on the breach, gravel and dam up the narrow entrance of the other. While they imagine they comprehend and encircle Nature in a Girdle of their own weaving, and know all the intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues of indiſcernible Wheels, as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the face and outſide of the work: Take but the leaſt part of this Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <pb n="122" facs="tcp:104697:70"/>in pieces; You will at once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire their folly, and the fearful Art ſhut up in ſo little room; and that all this unaccountable workmanſhip, and coſt is laid out on him, who ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>values and abuſes his Makers Wiſdom, and bounty ſtill waiting upon him. For it is an inceſſant miracle that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs the Creation, and maintains our lives with the even uninterrupted pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſo many curious Wheels and Motions, as we turn upon; the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringing of the leaſt whereof may diſſolve the whole order, break the chain which links all together, and put a full ſtop to the work and life of it. So little do they underſtand of their own dreadfully organiz'd Frame, and but juſt nothing how their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acts that by which they are become ſuch Monopolizers of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>Did they not reſt on ſome aiery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of the phanſie, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring one part of the Creation with another, blending the Originals, paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <pb n="123" facs="tcp:104697:70"/>and periods of ſeveral beings with the pleaſant power of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; did not ambiguous terms, and ſome bold defiances againſt Heaven, engage and confirm them; they would confeſs a Providence: and would they conſider and attentively examine themſelves, and the works of Time and Nature (which word retains with me it's innocent power and ſubſerviency) they would certainly acknowledge the hand of God in all this. A light and deſultory glance upon the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion puffs up Scioliſts, with an opinion of their omniſcience; but who ever ſeriouſly, conſtantly, intimatly acquaints himſelf with any part and paſſage thereof, ſhall behold ſuch amazing my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of infinite Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, as will reduce him joyfully to reſolve all into that Primary Great Mover, and Ultimate Center of All.</p>
               <p>Of whom to have any mean and unworthy apprehenſions is as impious, as the conception it gives to Atheiſm <pb n="124" facs="tcp:104697:71"/>can make it: So that what repreſents God leſs adorable in his Goodneſs and Juſtice, thereby deſtroying the hopes of an invited and willing duty; or takes off our obligations, and diſpenſeth with our leaſt indulgencies and relaxations; ought to be the abomination of our conceptions, as much as they be the direct contradiction of the Nature of God, and cleareſt manifeſto's of his Will. Thoſe ſeem to be the moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Apprehenſions of the Divine Attributes, which debaſing man moſt, do poſſeſs the Soul with a pure Love, and awful dread of that Glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, which our weak intellectuals can more ſecurely contemplate in the reflex, than the direct eſſence and acts of tremendous Perfections.</p>
               <p>Though Providence appear writing it ſelf every where, with the point of a Diamond darting a Sun-beam; Yet we endeavor to puzzle our interpretations and acknowledgements of it with our confuſed ſhallow and biaſſed notions, impeaching the equity of the great <pb n="145" facs="tcp:104697:71"/>Ruler of the World. But may I adviſe ſuch ſubtle diſputants, and aggreived peeviſhneſs, to await the Judgment of the laſt day, not doubting but that all the moſt bleſſed Attributes will be then vindicated from the ſilly intereſts, petty arguments, and calumnies, with which wretched Creatures aſperſe their Great Maker and Judge, darkning the ſecret Counſels of the Almighty, with words that want ingenuity and candor, no leſs than knowledge and wiſdom.</p>
               <p>The Meditation of thoſe ſummons to a General Account yields me ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfaction to the curioſity of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and inquiſitive man, which that day will afford. How far would not an active prying brain travel, to make a faithful collection and relation of the Hiſtory of the whole World? even to an <hi>Amara</hi> for the fragments of <hi>Livy,</hi> and as far for the Supplements of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> would ſome venture. What la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor and price, nay, fraud is thought too great to unlock ſome Cabinet Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, <pb n="126" facs="tcp:104697:72"/>perhaps thoſe no otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our times, than for the high opinion they left of their influences upon their own; with the notable aims and inſtruments of their manage (in whoſe breaſts they died) would be the ſweat of many brains to recover, and embalm, with politic remarks of their own, from putrefaction in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</p>
               <p>This may be no ſmall inducement, conſidering our daily Inſpection and bold cenſures and examinations into the lives, actions and relations of all that are round about us, and the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts we make of all events; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn us the greateſt care of our own particular duties: that ſo we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unconcern'd and acquitted in that great Rendezvous of ſpirits; and look for that bleſſed day with deſires, and expectations to receive in it a full nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, and faithful Hiſtory, of the lives and moſt famous actions of all Mankind: when we ſhall behold with what apprehenſions and Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <pb n="127" facs="tcp:104697:72"/>
                  <hi>Alexander,</hi> the <hi>Coeſars,</hi> and all the haughty Conquerors of the World will enter on that dreadful Theatre, and be brought alſo to the knowledge and admiration, of ſo many Noble Souls moſt deſerving of their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by their unvaluable and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed worth; who, trampling on the gayeties and follies of the World, with their own Rich Stock of Virtue and content, have ſilently (like the kind of ſubterranean fraternity of <hi>Bohemia</hi>) ſtoln into the dark and quiet of their Graves. All the Myſteries of Providence we are now ſolicitouſly and too curiouſly inquiſitive into, ſo far as concerns our revolutions, ſhall be there unfolded; and of Propheſie alſo, that we are ſtrangers unto, as to the manner of their accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>For may I have leave to ſuppoſe, many obſcurities, in the laſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly miſtaken Revelation of Futuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, cannot poſſibly be brought down to our lower Stage of Earth, in the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:104697:73"/>dreſs they are there repreſented. I ſhould rather ſuppoſe great part of thoſe viſions of the boſom Evangeliſt to figure out the State, Glory, and Polity of the Great Court and Council of Heaven, giving diſpatches and orders to our Affairs below; which both ſpeaks the care, and conſultations (as I may phraſe it) our Maker graciouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines us withal: And ſomewhere it ſeems to me, not unlike the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, wherein the wicked King of <hi>Iſraels</hi> ruine was reſolved. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering ſo much of the hiſtory thereof acted in Heaven, within the Veil (as I may ſay) of the Temple; and our ſucceeding revolutions to be but the immediate conſequents of thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Conclave reſults; and that Angels are Miniſters of State to the moſt High, and Guardians of Perſons, Nations, and Places; with Reverence due to the <hi>Arcana</hi> of the Empire, I ſhould the rather retain this Opinion. For were it alſo neceſſary to take place in our clear revealments of <pb n="129" facs="tcp:104697:73"/>knowledge, or of uſe and influence on our practice, I am aſſured, it would as clearly and fully anſwer the name it bears unto us; unleſs that alſo be to be underſtood, of what remains to be uncovered and revealed in after times.</p>
               <p>Without breach however of Faith, and obedience unto the divine diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Let us wait the opening of theſe grand Truths to us, ſo far as is fit for the Courtiers and Favorites of Heaven to be acquainted with them. But if the greateſt part of its Hiſtory be by its accompliſhment to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, the World has a duration beyond what we ordinarily allot it: And they are to be reprehended who think their own Age ſo great a portion of Time, and of ſuch eminent regard; That there ſhall be no great inſtance of extraordinary moment, which they will not bring down to be born there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: and that their own perſons and concerns are ſo wholly the peculiar care of divine benignity and conduct, <pb n="128" facs="tcp:104697:74"/>that there is no eie nor hand of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs watching to be favourable to the reſt of the Family (which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate tincture of the ſpirit of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm) ſo that if they feel any preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures or contradictions, the current of Providence muſt be ſuppoſ'd at a ſtand, and no leſs than fire from Heaven fetch'd down, to reſcue their pittiful proper Concerns: If the times they live in prove favourable, they gild them over with ſuch tranſcendent Glories as muſt make them outſhine and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verweigh all other: But if they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter deſerved or but ordinary dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties; eſteeming themſelves the only true Gold of their Age, for whoſe refining theſe Tryals are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, they will not want the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of heating the Furnace hotter than in thoſe famous Perſecutions, when the Church was yet in the mint: In the midſt whereof they are ſo far from the Doxologies of the Primitive Martyrs; that a meek Chriſtian would judge their mouths had contracted the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:104697:74"/>whole fire, and that their Tongues only were under the ſcorching heat of tormenting Flames. But if thorough various emergencies they land on a good old age, upon the ſecure brink of the Grave; as if when their pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts are over, there was nothing more to be acted on the world, and it became inſignificant when they are to be left out: They unwilling to ſpare their beloved Carcaſſes the time of a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs life (much leſs ſo long as theirs have been under divorce from the flood) preſently deſign with cruel Nero's wiſh the concluſion, (if not confuſion) of all the reſt of mankind; haſtning the Funerals of the Univerſe upon their own, that nothing may retard their private hopes and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: not reckoning up the Excellency of every member to reſt in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of the whole body; which conſidered extenſively, would enlarge the latitude of our converſe and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Charity.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:104697:75"/>
               <p>If then theſe will be perſwaded to attend the infinitely wiſe motions of their Maker, we may gueſs by them, the Worlds age not ſo full of the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated ſymptoms of its ſeneſcency: Take but that one Intention, and the only for which the Creation ſeems to have been raiſ'd from its nothing; the grand work of mans redemption: wherein the Power, Wiſdom, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Almighty concur, to give us an evidence of all engaged for our redreſs: to the deſign whereof ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſively myſterious, to the work of it wonderfully gracious; All we know or can deſire beſide, is but Vain and Deſpicable: and the whole not worthy nor able, to be the ſhell of this ineffable tranſaction of mercy. Yet this we ſee not till a full expired Period manifeſted; Heaven permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome thouſand of years to ripen its birth, and ſo long keep off the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and longing of the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So that if it ſhall now pleaſe the only Wiſdome, to prolong this free <pb n="133" facs="tcp:104697:75"/>exhibition of Grace, and repleniſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very corner of Earth with the joyful viſits and abode of this light; That a day may ſpring forth proportionate to the ſhades and twilight of a long morning (dwelling in the dawning Eaſt of the Jews) by a culminating high Glory, and the leiſurable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of Time: if it have not yet aſcended its Meridian Luſtre, and greater beams and glories will be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaied unto after ages; if there be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a ſucceſſion of greater wonders, in which the whole world ſhall at once ſee and adore the Scepter of their Redeemer, and every part of it feel the power glory and Joy of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from Death and Hell: Why ſhould our evil eie envy this happy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of Light, and the munificence of our Lord? Why ſhould we bind up the hands, and reſtrain the ſweet influences of Heaven? Rather may we ſuppoſe that this late manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was no Niggardice to the Happineſs of man; but that it will be extended, <pb n="132" facs="tcp:104697:76"/>with the moſt free and open effuſions and largeſses of divine bounty.</p>
               <p>But I dread to approach theſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries with a bold hand and profane foot; and adviſe others againſt time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratious putting forth theirs to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ark, which needs not humane ſupport. For we may be ſo miſtaken in our dark conceptions, and ſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; as to run into a quite contrary reſolution, of the egreſſes and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Deity. And all the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we take in meditation on theſe hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den verities, will be moſt allowable; which makes way for our enlarged ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions and adorations of Infinite Goodneſs. And indeed a wiſe man is not ſo much in proſpective, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing Futurities; as (if I may uſe the word) in a continued Retroſpect, here he may attain certainty in his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things Paſt; a ſober conject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure of the following, an inſight into himſelf ſeeing the Errors overſeen; and ſetting up a fair rule for the time to come.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:104697:76"/>
               <p>But I would not be thought all this while apologizing for Chriſtianity, eſpecially to thoſe great Souls, who by their ſolemn initial Vows, more ſpecial obliges, and all the marks and bonds of their Nobility are engaged to defend the honour thereof with their utmoſt perils. For notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that Sarcaſm of railing <hi>Julian</hi> to the complaints of the poor perſecuted Chriſtians, To you it is given to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer: I am confident the greateſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the mad world cannot prevail againſt this greateſt Truth.</p>
               <p>I might ſpend Volumes, to give you the Arguments our Religion defends it ſelf withall. While Reaſon and the tongues of men and Angels can ſpeak, they cannot be ſilent nor want demonſtrative juſtifications, of that Goodneſs, which form'd them to a communication and declaration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Chriſtianity (for I will not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and weaken it into factions) has of late been ſo powerfully vindicated, that Atheiſm can find out no new ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion, <pb n="136" facs="tcp:104697:77"/>which has not been beaten down, prevented and obviated. And may that Tongue be for ever uſeleſs, which will not ſpeak in defence of his glorious Maker: Our Profeſſion ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuffered of late by oſtentation of thoſe who had no Religion; may not another Thief come on this hand, and ſteal away that neceſſary Declaration and maintainance of our Faith and hopes, in too nice and modeſt Conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the truly devote Soul.</p>
               <p>I may fear a treſpaſs on the Labors and Victories of our late Crowned Champions of Chriſtianity; whoſe Learning and Piety will render this our Age notoriouſly famous, by the challenges they have anſwered of bold impiety. Nor can I quit my ſelf per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly in the rules and method of my diſcourſe; wherein I have rather ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the liberty of a Letter (and pray allow it to be like what it was born) the reſt is moſt of the notions, and long retained Sentiments of my own mind. And I believe would every <pb n="137" facs="tcp:104697:77"/>one turn over thoſe of his own Brain, many would be found ſo connatural to the being of the Soul, and Truth it ſelf: and thoſe in a diſtinct Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter from others legible: that I may imagine, as God has given each its ſpecific Spirit, ſo by differing Ideas this Principle is ſtamped and viſible upon every one: for we ſee a Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of all faculties and capacities di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing the minds of men, God revealing himſelf alſo according to the module of our Intellectuals; Yet ſo, as all confeſſe and read this one great Truth of his Eſſence, though in various impreſſions on the Soul.</p>
               <p>And that our conceptions of the Exiſtence of a Deity ſo much differ, deſtroies not the reality of what we diverſely apprehend. For bring into any Company (how great ſoever) ſome exotic and unknown Rarity, There ſhall not two agree perfectly, in all the modes of apprehending it; becauſe they have an eſſential Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity in the Faculties and Organs; as
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:104697:78"/>alſo a different ſtock and poſſeſſion of former Notions, to which they have recourſe, and refer this preſent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. If it be ſo in things incurring ſenſe, and where often no affection is touched; In this Pure Abſtraction from all ſence, and a notion that ſtirs up and works on every paſſion (which are all ſo variable, that none of them can ever be ſaid to appear again in their former Phaſes) no wonder that our Conceptions hereupon are as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe as our Souls and Countenances. But that all have their proper and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate notions of the being of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, I have greateſt reaſon to affirm; and confidently appeal to any perſon, whether he found not this, the only Indelible Principle upon his Soul, and after all his labour and art of oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if it does not yet fairly upbraid the ſponge?</p>
               <p>But this is a ſubject ſo copiouſly and methodically elſewhere, and by thoſe whoſe profeſſion has exerciſed their notions and parts, eventilated; <pb n="137" facs="tcp:104697:78"/>That I refer all mine to their Better directed, and therefore more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Speculations; only craving par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of thoſe our venerable Guids in Holy things, for any ſudden eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capes of long confined thoughts: which (without offence [I hope] to their conſecrate function) I have bundled up together to try how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneous they will be one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; and out of an humble hope to ſerve our hopeful Young Gentry, in the early meaſures they are to take of themſelves, and their Age.</p>
               <p>My whole deſign being, to gain but ſo favourable an influence on our young Nobleſs, now fairly bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoming; that outliving the noyſom Blaſts, and Morning Nippings of the dangerous Vices, their Age and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity are too obnoxious unto (no ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being more bewailed than that of the forward and tender Spring, killed by hard and unnatural Colds) They may yield a pleaſant ſhade and protection to Virtue, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:104697:79"/>the wholeſome and laſting Fruits thereof to ſucceeding Ages, flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing in the Cions of their Noble ſtock. May you therefore thus revive the high Renown of your Famous Grandfathers that their great Images may ſeem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd to live again in you the Genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Heirs of their Nobleſt Poſſeſſions. May you among all Nations recover, and advance the high Honour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of your dear Coutry. May the Glory and Puiſſance of your long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Soveraign be aggrandiz'd by the happy Aceeſſions of your wiſedom, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and courage: That the Saga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and Gravity of your Heads may ſeem to conſtitute under him a Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Council as large as his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions: The Loyalty and Generoſity of your Hearts, be the Beams and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Crown: The Valour and Activity of your Arms, his Forts, and Navy Royal: and your very private Families repreſent, and every where maintain the Splendor and Sanctions of a Regal Court. Then ſhall that good <pb n="114" facs="tcp:104697:79"/>hand of Divine Providence (which we have ſeen to riſe in a ſmall cloud, and ſuddenly ſpan ore the face of our whole Horizon, with amazing dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and deſolations) turn all its ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors upon our Enemies, and ſhowr down [as of old] the wonderful Deliverances of his Power and benignity upon us: which ſhall ſill up our furrows, with the bleſſed encreaſe of Truth and Peace. And
<hi>England</hi> clear'd of all its noxious weeds and Briars: under the conſtant irrigation of Heavenly muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence and care, ſhall no longer bear the folly ingratitude and curſe of ſo long <hi>Barrenneſs:</hi> but become a fair planted Encloſure of all its former Plenty and Proſperity.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:80"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:80"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE Principal HEADS, Herein contained.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>IDLENES</hi> Pag. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>PRIDE</hi> Pag. 26.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>INTEMPERANCE</hi> Pag. 37.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LUST</hi> Pag. 50.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>GAMING</hi> Pag. 75.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SWEARING</hi> Pag. 85.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ATHEISM</hi> Pag. 94.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:81"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104697:81"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
